<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the remarks on the Bishop of Derry's discourse about human inventions from what is objected against them in the admonition annext to the second edition of that discourse by the author of the remarks.</title>
            <author>Boyse, J. (Joseph), 1660-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 220 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4080</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1985</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12497880</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12497880</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62574)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 307:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the remarks on the Bishop of Derry's discourse about human inventions from what is objected against them in the admonition annext to the second edition of that discourse by the author of the remarks.</title>
                  <author>Boyse, J. (Joseph), 1660-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 88, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrence ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Joseph Boyse. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>King, William, 1650-1729. --  Discourse concerning the inventions of men in the worship of God.</term>
               <term>Boyse, J. --  (Joseph), 1660-1728. --  Remarks on a late discourse of William, Lord Bishop of Derry.</term>
               <term>Public worship.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62574:1"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE REMARKS ON THE BISHOP of <hi>DERRY</hi>'s DISCOURSE ABOUT Human Inventions, From what is Objected againſt them in the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition</hi> annext to the Second Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Diſcourſe. <hi>By the Author of the</hi> REMARKS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Lawrence</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62574:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62574:2"/>
            <head>To the Diſſenting Inhabitants of the Dioceſe of <hi>DERRY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInce the <hi>Biſhop of Derry</hi> has been pleas'd in his late <hi>Admonition</hi> to You, almoſt wholly to wave the <hi>Argument</hi> between Us, and to turn this Debate about your <hi>Worſhip</hi> into a Diſpute about <hi>Matters of Fact;</hi> nay, ſince he has frequently <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd to your own Conſciences for the Truth of what he has ſaid concerning you,</hi> acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That it wou'd be odd for him to think of impoſing on you in matters you know ſo well,</hi> and that <hi>he can only hope to prevail on you by the Integrity of what he ſaith,</hi> [See Admonition, <hi>p. 141, 148, 158, 159, 187, 188.</hi>] I thought I cou'd not reaſonably refuſe to concur with him in referring the deciſion of this part of our Controverſie to your ſelves, as the moſt competent and proper <hi>Judges,</hi> the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters controverted relating to your <hi>own</hi> or your <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> publick practices. And I may do it with the greater aſſurance, becauſe you'l find all that I now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert atteſted by your own Ministers, (beſides the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars relating to your Communions attested by ſuch as are Elders, or principal Members in your Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.) And as they must doubtleſs know theſe Matters better than the Biſhop can do, who is never preſent at their Worſhip; ſo I may justly preſume they are not ſo prodigal of their Reputation to the World, as to avouch ſo many things as True, which all their Hearers cou'd convict 'em of Falſhood in, if they
<pb facs="tcp:62574:3"/> were not. I confeſs 'tis ſomething hard that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſhou'd thus put 'em to this double labour, of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Practice by Affidavits, as well as defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it by Arguments. But when one is once engag'd with ſuch unreaſonable Diſputants, there is no decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning even ſuch drudgery as this. For ſince the things which the Biſhop objects against you are ſuch as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſuppoſes, <hi>will prove ſcandalous to all that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſtianity,</hi> If thoſe Objections be founded on palpable miſ-reports of your Practice, ſure the just esteem of ſo many Christian Pastors and Churches deſerves a modest Vindication. And indeed this Vindication had not been deferr'd ſo long, if the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of the Particulars to be enquir'd into had not retarded it beyond expectation; and your Miniſters were unwilling to run into ſo many Miſtakes as the Biſhop has unhappily done, by giving too haſty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of theſe Matters upon ſlight Informations. I ſhall therefore freely leave this part of our Debate (which now lies between the Biſhop and your own Miniſters) to your impartial Examination. And that thoſe excellent Churches you are Members of, may under the vigilant care of ſuch laborious Paſtors, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their external Reſt and Peace, <hi>by walking in the fear of the Lord, and in the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and thereby be both <hi>edify'd and multiply'd,</hi> is the hearty deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dear Brethren,</salute>
               <signed>Your affectionate Brother and Servant in our common Lord <hi>J. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62574:3"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THE <hi>Remarks, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>In this Admonition of the Biſhops we may conſider the Introduction, The Three Heads he propoſes to give an Account of: And The Reflections he adds on ſome Paſſages in the Remarks.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN the Introduction his Lordſhip is pleas'd to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate, tho' he does not venture directly to aſſert,<note place="margin">Admon. Octavo Edit. p. <hi>134.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That I have trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Opinions and Practices of the eſtabliſht Church in a paſſionate and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, in a ſcoffing and deriding manner.</hi> But ſince he has given no inſtances or proof of it, but referr'd it to the Reader's judgment, I ſhall with ſome confidence appeal to it alſo, as being well aſſur'd of the innocence of thoſe Papers as to this particular. Only, ſince he alledges a paſſage in his Diſcourſe againſt this way of treating Controverſies, I hope I may take the liberty of reciting one of my own, wherein I had taken care to obviate this Objection. 'Tis <hi>Remarks,</hi> p. 142. <q rend="inline">I do fully concur with him in his Advice, Not to treat one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62574:4"/> with ſcurrilous and unſeemly Reflections; but I hope he will not account thoſe ſuch wherein a Man is juſtly reprov'd for groſs miſ-repreſentations of other Men's Opinions or Practices, or a trifling Argument is not always treated with grimace, but ſometimes with the ſlight it deſerves.</q> Let but the Reader make me this reaſonable allowance, and I ſhall not be very fearful of his cenſure on this account.</p>
            <p>For the Three Heads which the Biſhop propoſes to give an account of relating to the Remarks, I ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine 'em in their order.</p>
            <p n="1">I. He acquaints us with the true Motive that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him to publiſh his Book, in which theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars are ſuggeſted.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He tells us how much Ignorance he found among the poor People, <hi>Inſomuch, as of</hi> 800 <hi>or more of the Diſſenters Communion, whom he perſonally diſcourst, he found not above four perſons that cou'd give any account of their Catechiſm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 135.</note> 
               <hi>and only two that cou'd repeat it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as to this matter of fact which the Biſhop pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes <hi>mov'd his compaſſion,</hi> I ſhall give him the Account ſent me by the Diſſenting Miniſters that are in his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe, and I hope that Chriſtian Charity which he ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten profeſſes, will render it very welcome to him, by aſſuring him that the generality of 'em are not ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as be has miſtaken 'em to be.</p>
            <q>We can give no Account how many perſons the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop has examin'd, but we know ſeveral whom he did examine that had the Aſſemblies Catechiſm, and could both give an account of it and repeat it, but would not, partly becauſe they heard him ſo enveigh againſt it, that they judg'd he queſtion'd 'em rather to affront than edifie 'em; and partly becauſe they were not free to ſubject themſelves to an Examination he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make as their Paſtor. But to evidence how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ground he had to ſuppoſe 'em ſo generally ignorant of their Catechiſm. If we may be allow'd to judge of other Congregations in the Dioceſe by thoſe two in in the Pariſh of <hi>Temple-more</hi> (alias <hi>Derry</hi>) where he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62574:4"/> reſides, and may be ſuppos'd to have examin'd the greateſt number. We can on good grounds affirm there are in thoſe two Congregations 600 who can give a good account of and repeat the Aſſembly's Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm: And we know of few in any of our Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations that cannot repeat the Creed, the Lord's Prayer, and the Ten Commandments.</q>
            <p>Now if this Account of their own <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who ſhould be beſt acquainted with their own People, be true, the Biſhop's Account is abſolutely incredible, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he has taken ſome extraordinary pains to pick out the moſt ignorant Diſſenters of his Dioceſe, that by them he might pretend to judge of the reſt. But any one that conſiders the genius of that People, and their particular diſſatisfaction with his Lordſhip, will be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily inclin'd to believe this genuine Account of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; That he has miſtaken their <hi>Silence</hi> for their <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and concluded they could not repeat their <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,</hi> becauſe they would not admit him to be their <hi>Catechizer.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>2. He computes, that there being but nine Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the Dioceſe, (and taking one Meeting-houſe and one Lord's-day with another) not 300 at each Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and there being 30000 Diſſenters in the Dioceſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 136.</note> it may be thence concluded, that only one in ten, or thereabouts, go to worſhip God any where on the Lord's-day. And this he profeſſes was a great grief to him.</q>
            <p>Now as to this matter of fact, I hope the Biſhop cannot take it unkindly that I endeavour to allay his grief, by offering him the following Account from the Diſſenting Miniſters in his Dioceſe.</p>
            <q>In the Pariſh of <hi>Temple-more,</hi> alias <hi>Derry,</hi> there are two Meetings, in which there will be found above 2400. who ordinarily worſhip God every Lord's-day. For tho' every one of theſe does not attend every Lord's-day, becauſe ſome of 'em muſt be left to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their houſes, yet theſe and more are ordinary Hearers, as the Miniſters of thoſe two Congregations
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62574:5"/> can undeniably prove by their Examination Rolls. Nay, the leaſt Congregation among us are ordinarily 600, and ſome above a 1000, that do worſhip God every Lord's-day together. So that where Miniſters are ſettled in Pariſhes, we do not know of one in 20, that do not ordinarily attend on publick worſhip. And for thoſe which the Biſhop ſaith have not been at any publick worſhip theſe ſeven years, we know none ſuch of our Communion. And for thoſe places that are not furniſht with Miniſters, the Miniſters that are ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſupply 'em as frequently as their work in their own Congregations can allow.</q>
            <p>Now if this Account be true, the Biſhop's Compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and the Concluſion he draws from it, is far e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from being ſo. And that there are yet ſome Congregations that want Miniſters, and can only have occaſional ſupplies, is much more their <hi>grief,</hi> who are doing all they can to remedy it, than it can be ſuppoſed to be his Lordſhip's, who does all he can to leſſen the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of their Meetings, by obliging his Tenants to ſuffer neither <hi>Miniſters</hi> nor <hi>Meeting-houſes</hi> to be upon his <hi>Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>3. The Biſhop pretends that his Book contains an Anſwer to what he found objected by thoſe of the Diſſenters,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 137.</note> that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd with againſt the ordinary Lords-day worſhip in the eſtabliſht Church, and that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd himſelf to what he had ſeen and known to be their Opinion and Practice.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 'Tis evident by Mr. <hi>Craghead</hi>'s Reply to his Diſcourſe, which Taxes him with the ſame Calumnies as the Remarks, that if thoſe Diſſenters he Convers't with, gave him that Account he pretends of theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; they were ſuch as underſtood not the known Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions or Practiſes of their own Teachers. As when they alledg ſo many Reaſons either againſt the lawfulneſs of all Forms of Prayer, and againſt joyning in publick worſhip where they are uſed, or againſt the publick reading the Scriptures, or againſt all bodily worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore if the Bp. had been ingenious in proſecuting what he now ſaith was his deſign, he ſhould have told us, that he intended
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62574:5"/> only by this Book to Correct the miſtakes of a few Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant People, that neither knew the Judgment of their Paſtors, nor the common Practiſe of the Congregations they Joyned with. And that he intended not to charge the generality of the Diſſenters, even not thoſe of his own Dioceſs with thoſe weak Opinions, and weaker Arguments and Objections which he endeavours to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and confute. But he has been ſo far from doing this, that tho in the Concluſion of his Book, he parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly Addreſſes himſelf to thoſe of his Dioceſs; yet in his very Entrance on his Subject, he undertakes to repreſent the Practiſe of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in general, or (in his own terms) <hi>of them that differ</hi> from the Eſtabliſh't Church. Nay, Where he ſuppoſes his charge only to be true of thoſe in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> he takes care to confine it to them; and therefore he gives us juſt ground to conclude, that where he mentions the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters without any ſuch Reſtriction, he is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as ſpeaking of the whole Body of them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the very Titles of his ſeveral Chapters, <hi>Praiſe, Prayer, Hearing, Bodily Worſhip, how practiſt among Diſſenters.</hi> And to Convince him of the Reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this, I ſhall put a Parallel caſe to him. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I ſhould write a Book about Eccleſiaſtical Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, how Practiſed in the Eſtabliſh't Church, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Diſſenters; and in the Account of the Practiſe of the Eſtabliſht Church, ſhould repreſent the ſad neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of all the Duties of their Function, both by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Prieſts; and accordingly ſhould charge the Biſhops with ſo many years Non-reſidence, in which there had been no Conſecration of Churches, nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of Children, nor Ordination of Prieſts, and the Prieſts with ſuch neglect of their Cures, as a great many in the Dioceſs of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Connor</hi> were Accus'd of: And ſuppoſe I ſhould particularly addreſs this Book to the late Biſhop and Clergy of that Dioceſs, Would his Lordſhip in this caſe think me Excuſeable from the guilt of Calumniating, becauſe I had particularly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt this Diſcourſe to them, when I have not in the Body of the Book confined my Accuſations to them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62574:6"/> but ſpeak all along of the faults of the Conformable Biſhops and Clergy in general, without any ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular limitation, or would he think me Ingenuous in producing ſuch Arguments, as the Biſhop and Clergy of the forementioned Dioceſs may alledge to excuſe themſelves, as the common Reaſonings of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Clergy: And yet, this were of the two more juſtifiable than the Biſhop's management of this Charge againſt Diſſenters, in which he has wronged the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality; even of thoſe to whom he now pretends that this Diſcourſe was confined, but much more the generality of the Diſſenters, againſt whom the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of his Book is levell'd without any Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I confeſs, to have told us plainly, that he only Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed the weak Diſcourſes he had met with among ſome few of the Diſſenting Laity, would have leſſened the Character of his Book, by ſuppoſing the cauſe of the Diſſenters to be little concerned in it; and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably the main Deſign of it, to blaſt the Reputation of the whole Party had been fruſtrated, by ſuch an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Confeſſion. But without ſuch an ingenuous Confeſſion, I do not ſee how 'tis poſſible to excuſe his Diſcourſe from untruth and diſingenuity; either in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to Diſſenters in general, what is peculiar to thoſe in the North of <hi>Ireland</hi> (as in the Head of Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Communion) or in aſcribing to a whole Party without diſtinction, ſo many Opinions, Arguments and Practiſes, as either none at all, or none but very Weak and Ignorant People are chargeable with; of which there are ſo many to be found in all Perſwaſions, that he who will meaſure the reſt of their Communion by them, can never want matter enough to expoſe the Wiſeſt and Sobereſt Body of Chriſtians whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. So that ſhould we allow the truth of all his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip here ſuggeſts, (<hi>viz.</hi> that he truly repreſents what the Diſſenters he Convers't with alledged to him.) It appears how little this ſignifies to clear him from the guilt of groundleſs Aſperſions.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62574:6"/>
            <p n="2">II. The Biſhop propoſes to ſhew, <hi>That I have granted the principal things deſigned in his Book.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Admon. p. <hi>138.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>As to theſe I aſſure him, That I ſee no reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract any of thoſe Conceſſions I have really made; and if they will be of any uſe to reconcile ſober Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to more charitable thoughts of each others Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, I ſhall rejoyce in it. But then I muſt deſire him not to ſtretch them beyound their juſt Bounds, as he ſeems to do in the following Particulars.</p>
            <p>Thus, Tho I have own'd Singing in Proſe (as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſtrict to Metre,) lawful in general, <hi>p.</hi> 10—yet as to the Practiſe of it in Cathedrals, whereby the main part of the Auditory is excluded from joyning in the publick Praiſes, through their incapacity to Sing them in Proſe; I have cenſur'd it as diſagreeable to the Apoſtle's Rule, of doing all to Edification, <hi>p.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>So, Tho I have granted Reſponſes in general lawful, yet I have cenſured the method of them in the Pariſh-Churches as applied to all Pſalms, as not only unſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural but unreaſonable and diſorderly, <hi>p.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>As to the 4th Conceſſion, Tho I think not thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptural Practiſes of Singing Pſalms by a Quire, and of Reſponſes in the Pariſh-Churches, to fall within the compaſs of what our Lord Cenſures, 7 <hi>Mark.</hi> 7. yet I think them a very defective and diſorderly way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; to which I judge the more Scriptural way pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis't among the Diſſenters far preferrable.</p>
            <p>For the 5th Conceſſion, Tho I grant, Praying with or without a Form in general undetermined in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet I do not think it only a matter of Conveniency: For I doubt not Praying with a Form is a Duty, to thoſe who cannot Pray without it; and I think 'tis ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to exclude neceſſary matters of Prayer by confining our ſelves to a Form, when we can Pray without one.</p>
            <p>From Conceſſion the 6th he draws a wrong Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which I had particularly obviated; <hi>viz.</hi> That becauſe God preſcribed a Form of Words to the <hi>Jews,</hi> in ſome extraordinary parts of Worſhip, therefore be does in particular command Chriſtian Paſtors and their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62574:7"/> Flocks to Pray to him in Forms, for that muſt be the ſenſe of his Lordſhip's Inference, if it be any thing to his purpoſe: For I have challeng'd him to produce any Form preſcribed to the Chriſtian Church except the Lord's Prayer, or any particular Command for the conſtant uſe of that in publick; and for its being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times us'd as a Form, the <hi>Weſtminſter-Aſſembly</hi> in their larger Catechiſm, declare their Judgment for it.</p>
            <p>For Conceſſion the 8th, I do not own (as his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip here alledges) that there is no reading of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the North of <hi>Ireland</hi> in the Winter Quarter; for tho this Exerciſe is in ſome places forborn during the Winter Quarter, yet it is not in all, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly but in one Meeting in all his Lordſhip's Dioceſs, the reſt continuing it through the whole Winter; of which I ſhall have occaſion to take notice afterwards.</p>
            <p>For Conceſſion the 9th, Tho I have owned that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Worſhip is commanded in Scripture; yet I have not owned, but Cenſured it as practis't by ſuch as bow towards the Eaſt, or Altar, or at the Name of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>For Conceſſion the 10th, Tho I do not condemn kneeling in the Act of Receiving as unlawful, yet I have ſhewed it to be diſagreeable to Scripture Example, and by the ſtrictneſs of the Biſhop's own Rule unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to, <hi>p.</hi> 123.</p>
            <p>The third thing the Biſhop propoſes, is to ſhew, <hi>That whereas there are ſeveral matters of Fact which he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, and I deny; the miſtake lyes on my ſide,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Admon. p, 141.</note> 
               <hi>notwithſtanding I impute them to him with great aſſurance as falſhoods,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What I have charged him with as untruths, in reference to the <hi>Diſſenters in general,</hi> it lies on me to make good; what relates to thoſe in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as I have aſſerted nothing but upon their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, ſo I can produce no other <hi>vouchers</hi> than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And ſure I need not produce any other, ſince their Teſtimony concerning their own Practiſe, muſt by all reaſonable Men be allowed to be of greater weight and credit than his Lordſhip's, who cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62574:7"/> to know ſo well as themſelves what is done by themſelves.</p>
            <p>This premis'd I come to examine the matters of Fact, wherein the Biſhop attempts to vindicate himſelf, tho they are but a ſmall part of what I have charged him with Miſrepreſenting.</p>
            <p>For the two firſt matters of Fact, I ſhall take the liberty to offer them in the ſame order, and in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words of his Diſcourſe, <hi>p.</hi> 83, 84. <hi>Edit. Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>But the moſt ſad and deplorable defect of your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this Duty, is the caſting out the reading of the word of God from moſt of your publick Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, directly contrary to God's Inſtitution and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance for the Inſtruction of his Church; inſomuch, that in many of your Meetings, ſetting aſide a Verſe or Two for a Text or Quotation at the Diſcretion of the Teacher, the Word of God is never publickly heard among them; this is matter of Fact and undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. And in all the Meetings of the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in a whole year perhaps there is not ſo much Scripture read as in one Day in our Church, by the ſtricteſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry I could make, <hi>Diſc. p.</hi> 83, 84. And <hi>ib. p.</hi> 84. The Diſſenters baniſh the word of God out of their Meetings.—Sure 'tis a ſad thing, That a Man may go to moſt Meetings many years, and never hear one entire Chapter read in them.</q>
            <p>'Tis here obvious, That his main and poſitive Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is, <hi>That the Diſſenters have caſt the reading of the Word of God out of moſt of their Meetings, That ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aſide a verſe or two for a Text or Quotation at the Diſcretion of the Teacher, the Voice of God is in many of them never publickly heard among them:</hi> And that <hi>a Man may go to moſt Meetings many years, and never hear one entire Chapter read in them;</hi> and this Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he more particularly fixes on the Meetings in the North of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In oppoſition to this Accuſation I had told him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Remarks, p.</hi> 92, 93.</note> 
               <q rend="inline">'Tis the general Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Diſſenting Miniſters in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for about three
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62574:8"/> quarters of the year, (for in the moſt, the Winter quarter is only excepted) to read every Morning an entire portion of Scripture, uſually a whole Chapter, at leaſt ſo much of one as they can go thro with in an Expoſition of half an hours length.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The very ſame matter of Fact; The Reverend Mr. <hi>Craghead</hi> has affirmed in his Anſwer, and more largely, without excepting the Winter Quarter, ſince in his Dioceſs all the Diſſenting Miniſters except one continue their Lecturing thro the whole year.</p>
            <p>Now this matter of Fact all the World muſt allow to be directly contrary to his ſevere charge; ſo that if it prove true, His Lordſhip could have no pretence to complain of my Reproving him, for offering ſuch <hi>bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac't untruths</hi> for <hi>undeniable matters of Fact.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let's then enquire what he hath ſaid to make good his Charge, and to that purpoſe he alledges Two Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <q rend="inline">That the Reading the Scriptures ſhould be ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, That the diligent Hearers may in a competent time be acquainted with the whole Body of them;</q> Whereupon he challenges me to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce one Meeting in the North where this has been obſerved.<note place="margin">Admon. p. <hi>144.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to this Allegation, 'tis evident, That it concerns not the matter of Fact in Diſpute at all, which is, <hi>Whether ſetting aſide a verſe or two for a Text or Quotation at the diſcretion of the Teacher, the voice of God is never publickly heard among them, and a Man may attend moſt Meetings many years, and never hear an entire Chapter read in them.</hi> For the Allegation concerns on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>manner</hi> of Reading them, whereas the Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuppoſes them not Read at all, except a verſe or two for a Text or Quotation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that I might juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſmiſs any farther Conſideration of it; but ſince the Biſhop gives me this occaſion to compare their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and ours, I ſhall ſuggeſt to him, That tho we Read not ſo much of Scripture as they in ſuch entire Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as whole Chapters, yet we Read the Scriptures more <hi>regularly</hi> then they, and a Man may ſooner hear them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62574:8"/> Read through in a <hi>Meeting,</hi> than he can in moſt of the <hi>Pariſh-Churches.</hi> To clear this I muſt premiſe, That in the generality of the <hi>Pariſh-Churches</hi> through the Kingdom, there is no Divine Service Read except on <hi>Sundays;</hi> Now if we conſult the Calender in the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> we ſhall find, That (excepting the <hi>Pſalms</hi>) there is never read from one generation to another, but about 104 Chapters of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and that in ſuch order or rather diſorder, as breaks the Coherence of the Sacred Hiſtory: So that a Man may if he lived to 80 years, attend the Publick Worſhip in moſt Pariſh-Churches all his Days, and never hear the 4th, 5th, 6th, 7th, 8th. Chapter of <hi>Gen.</hi> and ſo on. See the Leſſons proper for Sundays; and how is the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> Read? This <hi>Sunday</hi> we have the <hi>Matt.</hi> 1. and the <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. Read; the next Sunday the 8th of each, and next 15th. Four Months hence the 3d of <hi>Matt.</hi> and the 4th of <hi>Rom.</hi> So that in the generality of the Pariſh-Churches, the Scriptures are Read moſt confuſedly; ſo that the Hearers are incapable of obſerving the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Connexion of its parts; and in moſt Pariſhes, the far greater part of them is never read at all: Whereas in the Meetings, 'tis the general Practice to Read on a Book in order; and tho their Expoſition hinder them from Reading ſo large a Portion, (for which there is abundant Compenſation by their Expounding what is read from Parallel places of Scripture) yet they will in the courſe of ſome years be read all over, which they never are nor can be, in the generality of the <hi>Pariſh-Churches</hi> that are ſhut all the Week. But as this firſt Allegation had it been true, ſignifies nothing to the purpoſe 'tis brought for, ſo let us ſee whether the other be more conſiderable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Biſhop Appeals to our ſelves, <hi>Whether any of, our Miniſters ever read one Portion of Scripture, but what was either deſigned for a Text to a Lecture or Sermon or a Quotation. If any one pretend the contrary, he deſires me to name the time and place that he may reprove thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, which I affirm have ſo groſly impoſed on him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Admon. p. 144.</note> 
               <hi>but till the time and place be named, his Aſſertion he ſaith is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62574:9"/> literally true, and in a larger ſence then he expreſſed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I muſt deſire his Lordſhip to review this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and tell us, <hi>Whether it be literally true, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a verſe or two for a Text or Quotation, the voice of God is never publickly heard in their Meetings,</hi> when 'tis (as Mr. <hi>Craghead</hi> informs him) their ordinary Practice to Lecture every Lord's Day, and uſually to Read a whole Chapter, or divide a long one that's full of Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual difficulties. Is a whole Chapter or half <hi>a long one,</hi> only a <hi>verſe or two for a Text?</hi> Nay is it literally true, <hi>That a Man may go to moſt Meetings many years, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Hear an entire Chapter Read,</hi> when in the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of them he ſhall moſt commonly Hear a whole one Read every Lord's Day? But what does he mean, when he challenges me to name the time and place in which any entire Portion of Scripture was Read, but what was either deſigned for a <hi>Text to a Lecture or a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon?</hi> What is this to the matter of Fact that he Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed? For beſides that a Text to a Lecture is a new Phraſe; Is a whole Chapter or half a long one, only a verſe or two? Or is a whole Chapter never Read, becauſe 'tis always read with a deſign to Expound it? Nay, is this ſo <hi>deplorable a fault</hi> as he has ſuppos'd it that we never Read an entire Portion of Scripture without intending to illuſtrate the ſenſe of it, by comparing parallel Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures with it? (for that's all his Lordſhip can mean, by making it a <hi>Text to a Lecture</hi>) Is it not rather our great <hi>commendation,</hi> That the Scripture is always Interpreted as well as Read, and rather matter of Reproach to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that 'tis barely Read, without giving the People ſuch help to underſtand it? And ſhall our extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diligence be made our <hi>deplorable crime,</hi> and their ſloth ſo great a <hi>virtue?</hi> And upon the whole, would it not have been more ingenuous in him to own that his Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers had groſly impoſed upon him, then to perſiſt in ſo plain a miſtake, and then colour it over with an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology, the weakneſs and unreaſonableneſs whereof had been ſo largely and juſtly expoſed in that part of the <hi>Remarks,</hi> to which he has not yet thought fit to give any Anſwer?</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62574:9"/>
            <p>But tho' the Biſhop be in the wrong, as to the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of the Accuſation, he ſeems very confident of what he has ſaid to vindicate that <hi>Circumſtance</hi> of it, <hi>viz. That in all the Meetings of the</hi> North, <hi>in a whole year, perhaps there is not ſo much Scripture read as in one day in the eſtabliſht Church.</hi> This he pretends to prove ſo fully, that by his Computation there appears to be four times more Scripture read in the eſtabliſht Church, than in all the Meetings of the <hi>North.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">To this purpoſe he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to take my own Computation of half a Chapter read in each Meeting for three quarters of a year; and ſo in the nine Meetings in his Dioceſe he computes 175 Chapters and a half to be read in a year.</q>
            </p>
            <p>On the other hand, <q rend="inline">He computes 11 Pſalms and 5 Chapters, and ſo in all 16 Chapters read in the 42 Pariſhes in his Dioceſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Adm.</hi> p. 142, 143.</note> and conſequently in all 672 every Lord's-day.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Computation at firſt view looks like Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, but is indeed liable to manifold and juſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Biſhop here puts that ſenſe on his words that was not the plain and obvious meaning of 'em.</p>
            <p>Their obvious ſenſe is, That there is as much Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture read in every <hi>Pariſh-Church</hi> in one Lord's-day, as in all the <hi>Meetings</hi> in the <hi>North</hi> in a year. And there was good reaſon to ſuppoſe he intended 'em in this ſenſe, both becauſe 'tis but the <hi>ſame</hi> Chapters are read in every <hi>Pariſh-Church</hi> thro' the Kingdom; and becauſe, without this ſenſe, his Lordſhip's words left us wholly in the dark how to judge of the truth of 'em, when he never told us, whether by the <hi>eſtabliſht Church</hi> he meant all the <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or only thoſe in the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor gave us any Account what proportion the number of the <hi>one,</hi> or the <hi>other,</hi> bore to the number of the <hi>Meetings,</hi> without which Particulars none could judge whether his Aſſertion were true or falſe; or if true, whether any matter of reproach, or no? For perhaps in the whole Kingdom the number of Meetings is not much more to that of <hi>Pariſh-Churches,</hi> than that of 1 to 52. But,</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62574:10"/>
            <p n="2">2. If we allow his Lordſhip the ſenſe that he now puts on his Aſſertion, yet his Computation will appear much too <hi>Liberal</hi> on his <hi>own</hi> ſide, and much more too <hi>ſcanty</hi> on the <hi>Diſſenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Computation is too <hi>liberal</hi> on his own ſide. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. He takes a day, <hi>viz.</hi> the firſt of <hi>April</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, on which there were ſeveral <hi>Pſalms</hi> extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary us'd. For take the <hi>Pſalms</hi> one with another, about five is the proportion of what is ordinarily us'd every Lord's-day, and 'twas only caſual that eleven were then us'd, the eight firſt <hi>Pſalms,</hi> as well as the three other, being ſhort, and not above the proportion of four or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Chapters of five and twenty Verſes long.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He brings in eleven <hi>Pſalms</hi> as <hi>Chapters Read for Inſtruction,</hi> (about which alone the preſent Diſpute lies) whereas he himſelf ſuppoſes 'em to be us'd as <hi>Forms of Thanksgiving;</hi> and ſo does the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> in which theſe are not propos'd to be read as <hi>Leſſons,</hi> but <hi>ſung</hi> or <hi>ſaid</hi> between the Miniſter and People. So that by a juſt Computation there remains only the five Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters a day.</p>
            <p>And his Computation is as much too <hi>ſcanty</hi> on the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> ſide: For tho' I have drawn ſuch a Compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as he mentions, yet I have drawn it only as a Computation of what is read in an entire Portion; and indeed have drawn it much below the Truth: for there is more uſually a whole Chapter read, and in the Meetings of his Dioceſe none but one, make any Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Winter Quarter. But I was ſo far from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning this, as a Computation of all that is read, that I have, in the very words following thoſe he quotes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Remark.</hi> p. 93.</note> told him, <q rend="inline">That I look on his Charge to be ſo unjuſt, that if we take the Scriptures to be read whenever they are <hi>verbatim</hi> recited to the People, and ſo compute all the parallel Paſſages of Scripture that occur in their Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and Sermons, (in which both the <hi>N. C.</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in general, and particularly thoſe in the <hi>North,</hi> uſe not to be ſparing in their <hi>Concordances.</hi>) I ſee little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to doubt, but there is as much of Scripture read, or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62574:10"/> as much of the inſpir'd Word of God propos'd for the Inſtruction of the People in each Meeting, as in each Pariſh-Church. And this way of reading the Scripture I have ſhewn to be moſt agreeable to the Pattern and Practice of the Apoſtles, and of the Chriſtian Church in their time.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Why then would the Biſhop take no notice of this, which would have brought this Debate to a more fair and eaſie trial. For what is read this way among us, will amount to vaſtly more than what is read in an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Portion. For take one Lord's-day with another, we may by a reaſonable Computation allow, between the Portion read, and the parallel Texts in the Expoſition, a Chapter and a half. And if we compute two Chapters more to each Sermon, there will be every Lord's-day five Chapters and a half read; and I do not here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what Paſſages of Scripture occur in Catechizing, tho' thoſe will amount to a very conſiderable Portion, if put together. And for the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> he has no more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to bring them into the Computation, than I have to bring in all the Scriptural Expreſſions that occur in our <hi>Praiſes</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> which I have alſo ſhewn him are more agreeable to the <hi>directions</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to examine the Biſhop's preſent Computation, if we allow him his eleven <hi>Pſalms</hi> that are us'd as Forms of Thankſgiving, I hope he will allow us all that's ſtrictly <hi>read for Inſtruction.</hi> And that he may not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple my Computation, I'le only allow one Chapter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Portion read and the Expoſition of it; I'le on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compute two Chapters more for the two Sermons preacht every Lord's-day; and upon this Computation (which is really much leſs than is read) it will appear, That in nine Meetings, allowing a Chapter for the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, there is read in the three quarters of the year 351; and allowing two Chapters each Lord's-day in the year for their Sermons, there is read 936 Chapters in a year: both theſe joyn'd make up 1287. Whereas in 42 Pariſh-Churches the Biſhop computes (with the 11 <hi>Pſalms</hi> and all) only 672 Chapters; and if we ſhould add 42 Chapters more for their Sermon, (for few preach more
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62574:11"/> than once a day) this will make 714, which is a little more than half of what is read in thoſe nine Meetings by the former Computation. But if this Computation were drawn to the utmoſt of Truth on the Diſſenters ſide, (for ſince eight Meetings in his Dioceſe Lecture through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole year, there are 104 Chapters to be added to the account, and as the Biſhop reckons the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> we ſhould add all the Scriptural Paſſages that occur in our Thankſgivings) the Biſhop's account would ſtill appear the more wide from Truth. However, upon the loweſt Computation he is really miſtaken in this Matter of Fact, as he is apparently ſo in the foregoing, and has wrong'd 'em in the <hi>Circumſtance</hi> as well as <hi>Subſtance</hi> of his Charge.</p>
            <p>The third Matter of Fact which the Biſhop under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to vindicate, is his Aſſertion, <hi>That a Man may fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the Meetings of the Diſſenters all his life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſc. <hi>p.</hi> 82.</note> 
               <hi>and yet have no ſecurity, or hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſibility, of learning from their publick Teachings all the great Myſteries of his Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I have indeed cenſur'd as <hi>a groſs and ſhameleſs Accuſation,</hi> and therefore was the more oblig'd to prove it ſo. To that purpoſe I not only told him, <q rend="inline">That the peculiar Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion were the ordinary ſubject of their Sermons, but that once a year at leaſt they conſtantly went through all the neceſſary Articles of the Chriſtian Religion in their Publick Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing, in which the Diſſenting Miniſters in the <hi>North</hi> were ſo particular, as to Examine every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſon of whoſe knowledge there could be any occaſion to doubt.</q>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rem.</hi> p. 85, 86.</note> And ſure one would think if this be true, there can be no <hi>Modeſty</hi> in ſuch a heinous Accuſation, Let's then hear what the Biſhop has offer'd to Vindicate himſelf.</p>
            <q>
               <p n="1">1. He propoſes a Summary of the Principles of our Chriſtian Religion, drawn rather from the Kalendar than from the Apoſtles Creed, of which ſeveral Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles are omitted, becauſe his Lordſhip could find no Holy-days for 'em.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62574:11"/>
               <p n="2">2. He tells us their Miniſters have a certain time appointed every year for Teaching each of theſe My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That there lies no Obligation on the Diſſenting Miniſters to go thro' theſe Myſteries in any ſuch time, nor in their whole lives.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That he could not find upon Examination that their Miniſters had done it.</p>
               <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See Adm.</hi> p. 145, 146, 147.</note> He pretends that I endeavour to excuſe this by putting him to produce Scriptural Command relating to it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Now I would deſire him to review this, and tell us whether it ſignifie any thing to take off the plain Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence I have produc'd, of the injuſtice of his Accuſation, <hi>viz. That their people are in publick Teachings yearly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiz'd, in which Exerciſe all the Myſteries of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and particularly thoſe mention'd by his Lordſhip, are explain'd to 'em. So that 'tis impoſſible they ſhould attend their Meetings one year, but they'l have the opportunity of learning 'em.</hi> Is it not ſtrange that the Biſhop ſhould overlook ſo clear a Demonſtration againſt the Truth of his Charge, under this Head, to which it properly does belong? For if this be true, there needs nothing more to prove what he has ſaid to be ſo groſs a Calumny as I have repreſented it. His Lordſhip has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed thought fit to take notice of this in another place, <hi>viz.</hi> p. 149. where he dare not downright deny it, but would gladly inſinuate a ſtrong ſuſpicion againſt the Truth of it. His words are theſe: <hi>I leave this Matter of Fact with you, and know what you muſt conclude, and hope you will be ſo juſt to your ſelves, as to determine of what credit this Author ought to be in his Relations. I will not derogate from your Miniſters labours in Catechizing their people; but notwithſtanding their pains, there are ſome thouſands of Men and Women in this Dioceſe that profeſs themſelves of your Communion that were never Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiz'd by 'em, &amp;c.</hi> Now either he means there are ſo many Perſons that were never Catechiz'd in thoſe places where Miniſters are ſettled, or in thoſe where there are none. If he mean the latter, What's this to the purpoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62574:12"/> if it were true, as I do not find the Diſſenting Miniſters in his Dioceſe think it credible; if he mean the former, they do declare, <q rend="inline">They know of none that were never Catechiz'd where there are Miniſters ſettled; but all are ordinarily examin'd once in the year, if not oftner. So that if any ſuch remain ignorant, 'tis not for want of their pains to inſtruct 'em.</q> And ſince he leaves this Matter of Fact with 'em, to be determin'd upon their ſerious conſideration, he may eaſily ſee how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary their Judgment of it is to his; and if he would yield to their Teſtimony concerning their own Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, I hope he'l be convinc'd there is ſome Credit due to my Relations, but none to his raſh and miſtaken Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations.</p>
            <p>But beſides that the neceſſary Principles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are yearly explain'd in the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> I have told him concerning the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in general, that tho' they have no other <hi>Rule</hi> to direct 'em herein than that of the Holy Scriptures, yet they do in their Sermons moſt frequently inſiſt on the particular Myſteries of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and can appeal to their People as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes thereof. And that this is true concerning the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Miniſters in his Dioceſe, he may find Mr. <hi>Craghead</hi>'s Account in theſe words,<note place="margin">P. 75, 76.</note> relating to the fore-mentioned Charge. <q rend="inline">I declare upon certain knowledge, that what he has aſſerted is a moſt unjuſt Imputation, for which he has reaſon to ask forgiveneſs of God; and I do appeal to many Thouſands now living, who are ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily witneſſes to the contrary; and many of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Perſwaſion know the contrary. With what Peace of Conſcience can any Man thus impoſe on Strangers, and impreſs future Generations with that which is ſo far from Truth! it being publickly known that we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily and orderly go thro' all the Heads of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith in our Publick Sermons.</q> And what if this be nor particularly preſcrib'd by the Directory? will it follow that 'tis not done? Or is not the Scripture a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Directory for that purpoſe? And whereas the Biſhop inſinuates this ſuſpicious Argument of our neglect,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62574:12"/>
               <q rend="inline">That he has ſeen many Sermons printed by our Party, and yet does not remember above two or three on theſe moſt neceſſary Subjects, (<hi>viz.</hi> the great Myſteries of our Religion).</q> Is it not hence evident that he ſpeaks at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of matters that he has little or no knowledge of? For I doubt not that inſtead of two or three, there are above two or three hundred Sermons publiſht by N.C. Miniſters on the principal Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion, (including thoſe that he has mention'd). What does he think of the firſt Collection of Sermons in the <hi>Morning Exerciſe</hi> on the principal Heads of Chriſtian Doctrine? Nay, ſome Divines have printed a large Body of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on the particular Heads of the Aſſemblies Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm; 176 of Mr. <hi>Watſon</hi>'s are now extant. How many of thoſe Myſteries are fully treated of in the large Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of Dr. <hi>Mantons</hi> and Mr. <hi>Charnock</hi>'s Sermons? Not to mention Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s, Mr. <hi>Ant. Burgeſſes,</hi> Dr. <hi>Bates</hi>'s, and many more. So that if the Biſhop have met with no more than two or three, 'tis only becauſe he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver converſant in their Writings. But why then ſhould he throw about ſuch ſevere Reproaches in the dark, and cenſure with ſuch aſſurance what he is ſo entire a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to, and what any, that ever was in the leaſt acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their Writers, can ſhew him his ignorance and indiſcretion in? And if the Conformiſts have printed more, 'tis no wonder, when the Preſs has been more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to them, and they have had greater advantages for appearing in Publick.</p>
            <p>And is it not ſtrange the Bp. ſhould pretend that I alledge what he quotes (<hi>p.</hi> 146, 147.) as an excuſe in this matter, when I expreſly diſclaim the alledging of it for that end, becauſe we need no excuſe, and only produce it as an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument <hi>ad hominem,</hi> which he was concerned to anſwer on the Principles he had laid down? So that upon the whole, the Bp. is oblig'd in all reaſon to do us right in this point, by owning ſo unhappy a Miſtake, and wiping off an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion, which as 'tis manifeſtly untrue, ſo 'tis highly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to the Reputation of his Brethren; ſince if it were believ'd, no Man that has any concern for his own Soul, would truſt it to their Paſtoral conduct,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62574:13"/> who are ſo groſly negligent of ſo neceſſary a Duty.</p>
            <p>The next Matter of Fact is, the Biſhop had affirm'd <hi>That not One in Ten of the Diſſenters Children get their Catechiſm by heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſc. <hi>p.</hi> 83.</note> 
               <hi>nor One in Five hundred retain it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the contrary I ſuggeſted, <hi>That I believ'd upon a more accurate trial, he would find that as many of the Diſſenters Children have got it by heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rem. <hi>p.</hi> 87.</note> 
               <hi>as of others that have done ſo by the Church Catechiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To clear himſelf, the Biſhop here alledges, <q rend="inline">That he has, beſides grown People, Confirm'd near a thouſand Children, all above 13 years old, who could ſay the <hi>Church Catechiſm.</hi> And on the other hand, he tells us of many trials he made in whole Schools at a time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> among the Diſſenters, and found that the generality could not go above a leaf or two in it;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Adm.</hi> p. 47, 48.</note> and he doubts whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any at all after twenty retain it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now in Anſwer hereto, the Diſſenting Miniſters in his Dioceſe declare, <hi>That there are ſeveral Thouſands of their People, both old and young, that can repeat the whole Catechiſm. And how many there are in other Pariſhes may be in part computed from that of</hi> Temple-more, <hi>in which there are</hi> 600, <hi>or more, can repeat it.</hi> So that if his Lordſhip had ſo ill ſucceſs in his trial, 'tis to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted either to the <hi>ſullenneſs</hi> or the <hi>baſhfulneſs</hi> of thoſe he examined: For certainly their own <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhould know this matter better than he; and ſince he appeals to them, they declare <hi>That they are aſſur'd he is miſtaken in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come then to the fifth and principal Matter of Fact diſputed, <hi>viz. Concerning the frequency of Celebrating the Lord's Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to this the Biſhop had appeal'd to the Diſſenters in general without any diſtinction, <hi>Whether it were not a great thing among many of 'em, if once in a year or two a Communion be Celebrated in one of their Meetings; that among ſome, 'tis often omitted for ſeveral years together, and in ſome places for ten or more: and on this account ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62574:13"/> upbraids 'em with rare or no Communion as their peculiar practice.</hi> Diſc. <hi>p.</hi> 161, 162.</p>
            <p>In oppoſition to this Charge, I had told him, <hi>That for thoſe Meetings in</hi> England <hi>and the South of</hi> Ireland, <hi>where Paſtors are ſettled, the moſt of 'em conſtantly Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the Lord's-Supper once a Month, others once in ſix Weeks or two Months, and a few every Lord's-Day, &amp;c.</hi> From whence I inſert'd the injuſtice of this Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſince the generality of the Diſſenting Miniſters ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate this Ordinance much more <hi>frequently</hi> than the generality of the Pariſh Miniſters; and their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are ordinarily more <hi>numerous,</hi> as well as more <hi>frequent,</hi> than thoſe in the <hi>Pariſh-Churches,</hi> allowing for the proportion which the <hi>Number</hi> of the Diſſenters bears to that of the <hi>Conformable</hi> Laity.</p>
            <p>And now let us conſider what the Bp. replys to this.</p>
            <p>Firſt he ſays <hi>He is not much concern'd in it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Adm. <hi>p.</hi> 155.</note> 
               <hi>having addreſt himſelf to thoſe of his own Dioceſe.</hi> Anſwer, Can his Lordſhip with any reaſon pretend that he has aſſerted this only concerning the Diſſenters of his own Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe, when he does not only in the very entrance of his Book, propoſe to examine the ſeveral parts of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as they are practis'd by <hi>thoſe that differ from the eſtabliſht Church,</hi> or (as in the ſame <hi>page</hi>) by <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Diſſenters</hi>—See <hi>Diſc.</hi> p. 8. —But gives this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chapter the Title of, <hi>The practice of Diſſenters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout frequency of Communicating.</hi> But of this I have ſaid enough already to ſhew him the unreaſonableneſs of this Excuſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He inſinuates theſe Arguments againſt the probability of it: <q rend="inline">If this be true, (ſaith he) their practice is much alter'd from what it was formerly: For when the Churches were in their hands, it was quite otherwiſe. St. <hi>Warburgh</hi>'s was a conſiderable Pariſh in the heart of <hi>Dublin,</hi> but had not the Lord's-Supper adminiſtred in it for Twelve Years; and I have heard the like of ſome other Churches in <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> at that time. I find the ſame obſerved concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> from the Year
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62574:14"/> 1648 to 1660. <hi>Antiq. Oxon.</hi>
               </q> And he adds, that he was told, <q rend="inline">That the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in <hi>Waterford</hi> did not Communicate above once a year before the Troubles, if ſo often.</q> 
               <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 155.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For what was practis'd either in <hi>Dublin</hi> or <hi>Oxford</hi> in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s time, I neither know, nor am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned with. But for this Aſſertion of mine concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preſent practice of thoſe Meetings of <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>South</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in which Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors are ſettled, I need no <hi>Vouchers</hi> at all. 'Tis a Matter of Fact as eaſily known as our Publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies are, and what we can produce as many <hi>Vouchers</hi> for as we have ordinary <hi>Hearers,</hi> there being always publick notice given of our <hi>Communions.</hi> And if the Biſhop diſpute this Matter of Fact, he may next di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, whether our Senſes may be truſted in what we daily ſee and hear. For what he alledges concerning the practice of Diſſenters in <hi>Waterford,</hi> of which he ſaith <hi>he had opportunity to enquire,</hi> it will appear by the account given me by Mr. <hi>Sinclare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See his Letter in the end.</note> who was at that time their Miniſter, that either his Enquiry was very ſlight, or his Informers very ignorant of the Matter; and that he has been as unhappily impos'd on by 'em, as I ſhall now ſhew him he has been by thoſe on whoſe credit he has related what is practis'd in his whole Dioceſe.</p>
            <p>'Tis evident then he has wrong'd the main Body of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in this Charge of their <hi>rare or no Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there are ſome things relating to the practice of the Diſſenters in the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> which I have aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and which the Biſhop does very poſitively conclude me miſtaken in.</p>
            <p>I had told him from their Information, <q rend="inline">'Tis ſo far from being true, that 'tis rare if once in a year or two a Communion be celebrated in their Meetings; that 'tis univerſally uſual in every Meeting where an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd Miniſter is ſettled, to have the Lords-Supper adminiſtred conſtantly once a year, and twice in the larger Towns. That when the Sacrament is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62574:14"/> in one Meeting, 'tis uſual for moſt of the Members of neighbouring Pariſhes to frequent it. That the moſt ſerious People among them Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate four or five times a year; and have the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of doing ſo 10, 12, or 15 times, if they will take the advantage of Receiving it in Neighbouring Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And what I have here affirmed is the very account ſent me from the Reverend Mr. <hi>Adair</hi> of <hi>Antrim,</hi> with the approbation of that Meeting: and I ſhall here ſubjoin this following Obſervation he makes in his own words; <q rend="inline">You know alſo, That where the Sacrament is Adminiſtred, two parts of the Receivers are uſually ſtrangers; by which it is evident, that once Adminiſtring according to the cuſtom uſual a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians here, where they Communicate with each other in their ſeveral Congregations reſpectively, is equivalent to the Adminiſtring of it three or four times a year to each particular Congregation, where this way is not in uſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now as to this, the Biſhop tells us, <q rend="inline">He has as good opportunity of informing himſelf in theſe matters, as any can have, and has been as diligent in his Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in his Progreſſes through his ſeveral Pariſhes, and on all occaſions as he could; and he has the following Account returned him from many hands, and is ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied there can be no great miſtake in it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">In theſe laſt ſeven years the Lord's Supper has been Celebrated among you, in <hi>Derry</hi> twice, in <hi>Clander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mot</hi> once, in <hi>Ballindret</hi> once, at <hi>Ballikelly</hi> once, at <hi>Burt</hi> twice, at <hi>Ardſtra</hi> once, at <hi>Ahadowy</hi> once, in all nine times, (<hi>Admon. p.</hi> 151, 152.)</q> And <hi>p.</hi> 153. he adds a ſignificant reaſon why he cou'd not eaſily miſtake in theſe matters, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Becauſe their Sacraments are Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred with ſuch a concourſe of Spectators and Hearers, that they can hardly eſcape Obſervation.</q> (Tho by the way, why the Biſhop ſhould ſuppoſe this an Abuſe brought in by Popery, I do not underſtand; for I take it to be a very proper means of exciting in the <hi>Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> Pious deſires of becoming Communicants: And for the Practice of the Primitive Church in diſmiſſing all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62574:15"/> that were not Communicants when they entered on the Celebration of this Ordinance: I know of no other occaſion for it, than their care to conceal theſe Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of their Religion from the Pagans; a reaſon that we are not concerned in.)</p>
            <p>But now, If after all this diligent Enquiry, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's Informers have groſly impos'd on him in almoſt every particular of this Account: Nay, if the Account where it is true ſignify nothing to the purpoſe for which 'tis alledged, and appear highly diſingenious, then I hope he will think himſelf under ſome Obligation to diſtruſt thoſe <hi>Informers</hi> for the future, and will be more cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of aſſerting any thing on their Credit, to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of his Brethren.</p>
            <p>And here I would premiſe, That there is an inſtance of Diſingenuity in the Biſhop's Method of comparing the Practiſe of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> with that of the <hi>Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Church,</hi> too obvious and palpable to be over-look'd. In his accounts how oft the Sacrament has been Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in the <hi>Eſtabliſh'd Church,</hi> he goes no farther back then the time of his own Advancement to the See of <hi>Derry,</hi> which was ſoon after the Troubles; but in his Accounts how oft it has been Adminiſtred by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, he takes in ſeven years, tho he knows well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that for two of the ſeven at leaſt, both the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and People were ſcattered, and had no oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for Celebrating that Inſtitution; and yet he is ſo imprudent as to make this a great aggravation of their neglect; <hi>That ſome of thoſe ſevon years being times of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, required a more frequent Celebration of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Sacrament then ordinary;</hi> (See his <hi>Errata</hi> that refers to <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>l.</hi> 2.) as if he were ignorant, that ſome of their Miniſters were fled to <hi>Scotland,</hi> others ſhut up in the Walls of <hi>Derry,</hi> and their People ſo diſpers't, that they could not for any conſiderable time after the Raiſing that Siege make up any diſtinct Congregations again. And if the Biſhop alledge, that at leaſt the Diſſenters in <hi>Derry</hi> during the Siege ſhould have had it Adminiſtred, I would deſire him if he blame them on this Account, yet to be ſo impartial as to give the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:62574:15"/> there a ſhare in his Reproof; for thoſe I have deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to enquire upon the place, cou'd not learn that they Adminiſtred it any more than the other: So that thoſe 2 years of publick Troubles and Confuſion, ought in all reaſon to be ſhut out of his Account. And how unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate he has been in his particular and exact Account he now pretends to give, will appear by the following one that the Diſſenting Miniſters of his Dioceſs have after a very particular enquiry given of the year 87, 88, 91, 92, 93, 94.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">In the year 87, 88. The Sacrament was Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in <hi>Derry</hi> twice, in <hi>Donaghedee</hi> twice, in <hi>Drumrah</hi> twice, in <hi>Ardſta</hi> twice, in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rney</hi> twice, in <hi>Donagh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> twice, in <hi>Lifford</hi> once, in <hi>Glendermot</hi> once, in all fourteen times.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">In the four laſt years ſince the troubles, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was Adminiſtred.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">In <hi>Derry</hi> four times, in <hi>Burt</hi> thrice, in <hi>Ahadowy</hi> twice, in <hi>Ardſtra</hi> twice, in <hi>Ballindret</hi> or <hi>Lifford</hi> once, in <hi>Mahara</hi> once, in <hi>Ballikelly</hi> once, in <hi>Donaghmore</hi> once, in <hi>Strabane</hi> once, in all ſixteen times.</q> So that for the laſt Six years, in which there can be any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for requiring the Adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from 'em, it has inſtead of nine times been Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred 30. Nay, Tho we reckon the two years of the Troubles in which they had no opportunity, yet the year 88 falling within the compaſs of the ſeven men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by the Biſhop, they had it 22 or 23 times.</p>
            <p>But I have a more juſt and ſevere Challenge againſt the <hi>Sincerity</hi> and <hi>Candour</hi> of this Account, which the Biſhop's Informers have given him, <hi>viz.</hi> That they were not ſo honeſt as to acquaint him, that beſides the two years of Troubles, in a great part of the other years, ſeveral of thoſe Congregations had no Miniſters at all, whom yet he makes accountable for the Sacrament du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring 7 years together; whereas that Aſcertion of mine which the Biſhop here undertakes to diſprove, concerns only <hi>ſuch Congregations where Miniſters are ſettled.</hi> (For it were ridiculous to expect <hi>Sacraments</hi> where there are no <hi>Miniſters</hi> to Celebrate them.) Now beſides the two years of ſeven that are to be taken off from each Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62574:16"/> (for even <hi>Derry</hi> itſelf had no Miniſters from the year 88 till after the Troubles) the following Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations had no Miniſters for the years hereafter men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Glendermot</hi> or <hi>Clondermot</hi> had none at all ſince the Troubles, ſo that there has been a Miniſter there on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one year of the ſeven, <hi>Ardſtra</hi> had a Miniſter only two years ſince the Troubles, and in them two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but had no Miniſter at all till after the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. For <hi>Ballindret</hi> two Communions were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but both prevented by their Miniſters being viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Sickneſs, and 'tis a year ſince he died, ſo that only one Sacrament could be Celebrated ſince the Troubles. For <hi>Ballikelly,</hi> their Miniſter beſides long Sickneſs after the Siege of <hi>Derry,</hi> has been much in <hi>Scotland</hi> and elſewhere. For <hi>Strabane</hi> the Miniſter has not yet been two years there, and the true reaſon why the Sacrament was but ſeldom Adminiſtred there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, was (beſides the Bodily Infirmities of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter) chiefly the violence of Perſecution, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him out of that Pariſh.</q> And yet ſuch Blame the neglect, whoſe unchriſtian ſeverity was the cauſe of it. For the other places which the Biſhop has overlook't in his Account and I have added to mine, I muſt alſo add, <hi>That</hi> Mahara <hi>had but one Sacrament ſince the Troubles, becauſe they have had a Miniſter but one year; and the ſame muſt be ſaid of</hi> Donoghmore. <hi>For</hi> Donaghedee, Drumra <hi>and</hi> Urny, <hi>which had conſtant yearly Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before the Troubles, they have none of them had any Miniſter ſince.</hi> Now by this Account it appears, that according to what was practiſed where Miniſters have been ſettled, there would have been about 70 Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions Celebrated in the laſt ſeven years in the 10 Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings now mentioned, if either the want of Miniſters in places, or their Sickneſs, or the two years of Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Troubles, or the like extraordinary Accidents had not prevented. So that for the Biſhop not only to miſtake nine times for about twenty three or thirty, but to charge theſe rare Communions on their Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in Adminiſtring this Ordinance, when they were
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62574:16"/> wholly owing to theſe extraordinary occaſions fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd, is ſo highly diſingenuous and unjuſt, that he ought not to ſuffer thoſe that have ſo unhappily abus'd him in theſe matters, to paſs without a ſevere Reproof. For ſince the Diſſenting Miniſters in the <hi>North,</hi> on the account of the extraordinary pains they take to prepare their People for the Sacrament, celebrate it ſo ſeldom in each Congregation as once a year, there was the greater reaſon they ſhould not be wrong'd in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts given of their Practice. So that in this Matter of Fact, I hope the Biſhop will own and retract his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake.</p>
            <p>For what I aſſerted concerning the <hi>Sacraments being twice a year adminiſtred in the larger Towns in the North,</hi> was intended, and is true of <hi>Belfaſt, Carickfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> and <hi>Antrim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what I have aſſerted concerning <hi>their Members Communicating four or five times a year, is true</hi> of the moſt devout and ſerious of them; and ſo is it, <hi>That they may have the opportunity of Communicating ten, or twelve, or fifteen times a year, within ſome miles of their reſpective Habitations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This indeed the Biſhop concludes to be a great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake. <q rend="inline">Becauſe on this Suppoſition he thinks it will clearly follow, that not much above a hundred diſtinct Perſons have Communicated in the Dioceſe theſe laſt ſeven years. For four times 7 makes 28; and 3600 (which his Lordſhip computes to be the full number of their Communicants in ſeven years) divided by 28, gives about 128; but this can by no means be true: Therefore (ſaith the Biſhop) he is certainly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informed in this particular.</q> 
               <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 153.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The whole of this Computation depends on his two Suppoſitions, <hi>That the Sacrament has been Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred but nine times in ſeven years, and that one with another, only</hi> 400 <hi>have received at one time, and ſo</hi> 3600 <hi>in all.</hi> How great a miſtake the <hi>former</hi> Suppoſition is, I have already ſhewn; and how much greater the <hi>latter</hi> is, will appear from this one Paſſage, That in the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> of <hi>Temple-more</hi> alone, (aliàs <hi>Derry</hi>) including the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62574:17"/> two Meetings of <hi>Derry</hi> and <hi>Burt,</hi> there have Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated ſince the Troubles above 5000, which is above 1400 more than he ſuppoſes to have Communicated in all the Dioceſe in ſeven years. Nay, whereas he ſuppoſes, <q rend="inline">That near as many have received in the Cathedral, in three years paſt, as have Communicated with the Diſſenters in his whole Dioceſe in twice that time.</q> It appears that near 2000 more of the Diſſenters have Receiv'd in the ſame Pariſh, in about the ſame time, than have Receiv'd at the Cathedral, notwithſtanding the Sacrament being Adminiſtred there every Month (tho' by the way, the Diſſenters of <hi>Derry</hi> think he has ſtretch't the number of his Monthly Communicants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all juſt bounds, of which they can give very ſhrew'd Evidence.) Since then his Computation of the number of Communicants among the Diſſenters is ſo vaſtly wide from Truth, his Inference from it falls of courſe.</p>
            <p>For what I aſſerted concerning their having the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of Communicating ten, or twelve, or fifteen times a year, within ſome miles of their reſpective Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, the Biſhop concludes it to be a miſtake; <q rend="inline">Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there being but nine Meetings in his Dioceſe, tho' each Member ſhould communicate at each Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he could but communicate nine times a year, and muſt ſometimes travel forty miles for a Sacrament.</q> 
               <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 154, 155.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I might here juſtly enquire, Why the Biſhop ſhould think the Diſſenters of his Dioceſe ſo confin'd to it, that thoſe that live near Meetings in another Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe, may not take the opportunity of Communicating there. Does he think their <hi>Communion</hi> limited within the bounds of his <hi>Juriſdiction?</hi> But I muſt here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him, That this Aſſertion of mine reſpects the generality of Meetings in the <hi>North;</hi> and therefore the truth of it is to be eſtimated from thoſe parts where the main Body of the Diſſenters are to be found. Now he cannot be ignorant that they are moſt numerous in the Counties of <hi>Antrim</hi> and <hi>Down.</hi> And therefore ſince he is pleaſed to arraign the Truth of the Aſſertion, I ſhall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62574:17"/> give him the following Demonſtration of it, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Congregations that belong to the Meeting of <hi>Antrim,</hi> ſent me by the Reverend M. <hi>W. Adair</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Town of <hi>Antrim.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>I take <hi>Carn-caſtle,</hi> which is the moſt remote Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation ſave one Northward in our Meeting, and within twelve miles they may Communicate at <hi>Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narm, Blade, Ballimanoch, Coymer, Ballyraſton, Ballyclare, Carmony, Dunagor, Lorn, I. Macgee, Broad-Iſland, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricfergus</hi> twice, <hi>Temple-Patrick,</hi> and <hi>Carn-caſtle</hi> it ſelf. In all fifteen times.</p>
               <p>I take <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> which is the fartheſt of our Meeting Southward, and I ſuppoſe within twelve miles they may yearly Communicate above twenty times; <hi>viz.</hi> at <hi>Belfaſt</hi> twice, at <hi>Caricfergus</hi> twice, <hi>Antrim</hi> twice, <hi>Holywood, Knock, Kirk-donold, Newton, Cumber, Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linchy, Donachadee, Tonochneer, Danmurry, Lisbon, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nahilt, Bangor, Carmony, Temple-Patrick, Ballyclare, Ballyraſton, Dunnagor, upper Killade, lower Killade, Broad-Iſland,</hi> (which is within 11 miles.) In all 26 times.</p>
               <p>You may eaſily conceive that many places, or almoſt all in our Meeting which are towards the Centre, can have the Sacrament as often at leaſt, and generally oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than at <hi>Carn-caſtle.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>So that this Matter of Fact is true beyond all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, as I have aſſerted it, concerning the generality of their Meetings. And I am no way oblig'd to prove it, concerning every particular one in the remoteſt parts of the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, whereas the Biſhop had affirm'd in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <q rend="inline">That he could not compute that one in ten that go to their Meetings, ever Receive thro' the whole courſe of their Lives; and blames me for aſſerting the contrary, That there is not one in ten but do Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, except ſuch as are with-held for want of competent knowledge, or on the account of Scandal, (or I might here add, thro' their own Scruples about their preparation for it) as if this were a great Reflection upon 'em;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 154.</note> as if 19
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62574:18"/> in 20 were ignorant or ſcandalous.</q> This will appear to be a very miſtaken Account of this Matter, if we compare the number of <hi>Hearers</hi> in the two Meetings of <hi>Derry</hi> and <hi>Burt,</hi> with the number of <hi>Communicants.</hi> For their ordinary <hi>Hearers</hi> are about 2400. (Of which ſome part are ſuppos'd to be left at home every Lord's-day.) And yet in ſome of the Communions there ſince the Troubles, there have Communicated 984 Perſons in one of thoſe Meetings. So that we may compute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 1600 <hi>Communicants</hi> in both. Now tho' we allow a conſiderable deduction out of this number of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants,</hi> for the Strangers that may be ſuppos'd to have Receiv'd, yet the number of <hi>Communicants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing</hi> to thoſe two Congregations, compar'd with that part of their <hi>Hearers</hi> that are of Age to Receive, will ſufficiently demonſtrate that the Biſhop's Computation, <hi>That not one in ten Receive,</hi> muſt be very wide from Truth.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>generality of the Diſſenting Miniſters admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring this Sacrament far oftner than the generality of the Conforming Clergy,</hi> I did not, as the Biſhop here groundleſly ſuppoſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 151.</note> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert it concerning the Diſſenting Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but of thoſe in <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>South</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (which make up the generality of 'em) concerning whom 'tis too apparently true to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of being diſputed.</p>
            <p>And for their preſſing their People as much or more to it, if we may judge thereof by the ſucceſs of their Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, I think it paſt doubt, that take an equal number of <hi>Meetings</hi> and <hi>Pariſh-Churches,</hi> and according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Hearers in the one and the other, the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants</hi> are far more <hi>Numerous</hi> in the <hi>Meetings</hi> than the <hi>Pariſh-Churches,</hi> even tho' the former are far more ſtrict in their Admiſſions; and in the latter few are ever refus'd that deſire to come. Of which, if the Biſhop pleaſe, I ſhall produce him manifold Inſtances. <q rend="inline">And for what his Lordſhip affirms of their Sermons tending rather to deter poor weak Creatures from Receiving, than encourage 'em, by magnifying the difficulty and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62574:18"/> of the undertaking.</q> I know no ground he has for this Aſſertion, unleſs it be, that they endeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all that are groſly ignorant or ſcandalous from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning that Holy Inſtitution; and dare not encourage any to approach to it, but ſuch as in ſome meaſure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the nature of it, and do not by a ſcandalous Life contradict thoſe ſolemn Vows of Obedience which they there come to renew upon the memorials of a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Saviour.</p>
            <p>As for this laſt Matter of Fact, in reference to this Head about a <hi>reputed Elder,</hi> (or as in his <hi>Errata</hi> he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects it) <hi>Profeſſor of thirty or forty years of Age that never Receiv'd, but diſputes againſt it. Admon.</hi> p. 158. If the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop had pleas'd to name him, the truth of what he aſſerts might have been examin'd. But till we know who he is, we muſt let this matter lie undecided, unleſs we diſpute in the dark.</p>
            <p>So that in the whole of this Debate which relates to the Sacrament, the miſtake lies on the Biſhop's ſide, even in reference to the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Ireland;</hi> tho' he was oblig'd to make his Charge in his Diſcourſe good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Diſſenters in general,</hi> without any ſuch limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>For the Biſhop's being offended at my ſaying, <hi>That too many profligate ſinners are admitted to the Communion in the Pariſh Churches, and his charging me on that account with being uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and unjuſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Admon. <hi>p.</hi> 156.</note> 
               <hi>and challenging me to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance in ſome of his Dioceſe.</hi> I ſhall only reply, That I never yet met with any Perſon, before his Lordſhip, that doubted this Matter of Fact, and would not rather lament than diſpute it. For 'tis no more than has been frequently own'd by the beſt of their own Writers, and imputed to the preſent corruption or weakneſs of their Diſcipline. And tho' for naming particular inſtances I muſt beg the Biſhop's pardon, yet I will alledge what is equivalent to it. Does his Lordſhip think there are no profligate ſinners in Military and Civil Employments in <hi>England?</hi> and yet the Sacrament-Teſt obliges 'em all to receive the Sacrament, and he knows they are not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62574:19"/> ſcrupled when they come. Nay, were not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Soldiers ſince the Reſtoration in <hi>Dublin</hi> forc't to receive, and driven to it by their Officers with Oaths and Curſes, when nothing but the conſciouſneſs of their own wickedneſs deterr'd 'em? But as to this matter, I ſhall freely appeal to the common judgment of all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Perſons of his own Party, and fear not their Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on this ſcore; it being rather to be wiſh't, for the honour of the Reformed Religion, that the evidence of this Truth were leſs notorious. Nay, to the judgment of the ſame Perſons I would refer it, what ground there is for that Obſervation which the Biſhop tells us ſome have made, <hi>That Enmity to the eſtabliſh'd Religion and Immoralities are gotten on one ſide in too many inſtances, of it be meant of the Diſſenters.</hi> For beſides that, the Diſſenters have no Enmity at all to the eſtabliſh'd Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, having Subſcrib'd in <hi>England</hi> all the <hi>Doctrinal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> of it: That the Members of their Communion, compar'd with thoſe of the eſtabliſh'd Church are more generally guilty of Immoralities, is an Obſervation that I ſuppoſe will hardly paſs current with any but ſuch as have a faith to believe whatever their Intereſt or their Affection to a Party dictates to 'em.</p>
            <p>And ſince in reference to theſe Matters of Fact his Lordſhip requires me to produce my <hi>Vouchers,</hi> and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges me <hi>as writing upon none, or very partial Information,</hi> I ſhall ſo far comply with his Demand, as to produce the following Teſtimonial of the Truth of what I have ſaid, in reference to the practice of the Diſſenters in his Dioceſe, about whom our preſent Debate lies, from theſe three under-named Miniſters in his Dioceſe, who have diligently examined theſe Matters of Fact, and whoſe Informations communicated to me, relating to 'em, were, together with theſe Papers, review'd and approv'd by the whole Presbytery.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>WE the under-ſubſcribers having perus'd theſe Papers of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Joſeph Boyſe,</hi> drawn up in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to that part of the Biſhop of <hi>Derry</hi>'s Admonition which concerns the practice of the Proteſtant Diſſenters in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62574:19"/> this Dioceſe of <hi>Derry,</hi> do declare, Thoſe Informations which we have given him relating to it, and to which he here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, to be true; and hereby atteſt 'em as ſuch to the World, in order to our juſt Vindication from the miſrepreſentation made of thoſe Matters of Fact by the Biſhop of <hi>Derry.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Craghead</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Derry.</hi> 
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Andr. Ferguſon</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Burt.</hi> 
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Will. Homes</hi> Minister of <hi>Strabane.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And for his Lordſhip's farther ſatisfaction, Whereas one of the moſt remarkable differences between his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and theirs, relates to the frequency of Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Lord's-Supper (his account ſuppoſing them guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of very ſcandalous negligence) the Reverend Mr. <hi>Crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> has now in his hands, and is ready to produce when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his Lordſhip deſires it, particular Teſtimonials of this Account now given under the Hands of the Elders, and other Communicants of each Meeting. Nay, ſince the difference is moſt remarkable in reference to <hi>Derry</hi> it ſelf, which he affirms has had the Sacrament but twice theſe ſeven years, whereas they aſſert it has been admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred five times, (tho' for two of the ſeven years they had no Miniſter of their own;) and ſince the Biſhop's Friends pretends to undeniable Evidence for the truth of this Matter of Fact, I ſhall (to ſhame, if poſſible, his Informers out of their Confidence) trouble the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with the following Certificate, as a Specimen of what ſhall be produc't, if requir'd, from the other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>WE the under-named Subſcribers having heard and read of ſeveral things charged on the People of the Presbyterian perſwaſion of this City and Suburbs, now under the Pastoral charge and care of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Robert Craghead,</hi> and formerly of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Robert Rule,</hi> for the honouring the great God who is a God of Truth; and in oppoſition to all thoſe that have endeavour'd to poſſeſs the minds of ſuch as are Strangers to us, by ſpeaking or writing contrary to Truth; We do hereby certifie and give
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62574:20"/> under our Hands, and are ready to make it farther appear, if need be, upon Oath, that from the time of our being under the charge and care of <hi>Mr. Robert Rule,</hi> as our Pastor, which commenc't about the Year <hi>1672.</hi> till the time of his being neceſſarily call'd to go for <hi>Scotland,</hi> which was <hi>A. D. 1688.</hi> we had the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper duly Administred by him once a year in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; excepting thoſe wherein we were violently hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by the ſeverity of Perſecution. And more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly that the Reverend Mr. <hi>Robert Rule</hi> Administred that ſolemn Ordinance of the Lord's Supper to us in this place, in <hi>May 1687,</hi> and in <hi>April 1688.</hi> ſoon after which we were deſolate of any fixed Minister, till it pleaſed the Lord our now Reverend Pastor, Mr. <hi>Craghead,</hi> was fix'd among us in the year <hi>1690;</hi> and he has ſince then Administred this Sacrament in this Congregation the <hi>12th</hi> day of <hi>July 1691.</hi> On the <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>July 1692.</hi> On the <hi>14th</hi> day of <hi>May 1693.</hi> And on the <hi>22d</hi> day of <hi>July 1694.</hi> The cauſe of our knowledge hereof is, that we were Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Congregation, and did then partake of that Ordinance. And we deſire this may be compar'd with what is aſſerted in a Book, Entitled, <hi>An Admonition to the Diſſenting Inhabitants of the Dioceſe of</hi> Derry, &amp;c. <hi>p. 153.</hi> In Testimony of the Truth whereof we have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſet our Hands at <hi>London-Derry</hi> the <hi>25th</hi> of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1694.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Henry Long,</hi> Mayor.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Alexander Lekey,</hi> Mayor Elect.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Wilſon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hugh Davey.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hugh Eadie.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edward Brooks.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Lenox.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Horas Kennedy.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Harvey.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Andrew Garven.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Alexander Gourdon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Cowan.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Will. Mackie.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Harvey.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:62574:20"/>
            <p>And ſure if the Biſhop's Enquiries be ſo ſtrangely unſucceſsful in the very place where be reſides, we may juſtly infer how little regard is due to thoſe he made in other places. And upon the whole the unbiaſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may judge, what ground his Lordſhip had to ſay, in reference to all theſe Matters of Fact, That concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Truth of what he had ſaid, <hi>he need do no more than appeal to the Conſciences of Diſſenters. And that he must tell 'em, that what he wrote was from Sight, Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, or certain Information; whereas he ſaith I had my Accounts of things only at ſecond hand, and produce no Vouchers. Admon.</hi> p. 142. If he will ſtand to their Judgment to whoſe Conſciences he has appeal'd, he may eaſily foreſee his doom; for their <hi>Sight</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> are quite contrary to his. And ſince he obliges me to produce <hi>Vouchers</hi> for what I have ſaid, I hope hee'l either yield this Point, or produce as credible ones as theſe.</p>
            <p>But before I diſmiſs this Head, it will be requiſite to take ſome notice of thoſe remarkable words wherewith the Biſhop cloſes it, <hi>To conclude,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it were as eaſie to ſhew, That Mr.</hi> B. <hi>is miſtaken in every Matter of Fact, wherein he has charg'd me with falſhood, as in theſe; but the deſigned ſhortneſs of this Admonition will not give me leave to purſue 'em.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I hope the Biſhop will at length be convinc'd, That inſtead of vindicating his former <hi>Mistakes,</hi> he has only run into <hi>new ones,</hi> which are ſomewhat the leſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, becauſe he had ſo much <hi>time</hi> and <hi>leiſure,</hi> as well as <hi>advice</hi> to correct 'em. And ſince moſt of them are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry injurious to the good Name of his Brethren, common Juſtice ſhould have oblig'd him, inſtead of <hi>Reprinting,</hi> to have <hi>Retracted</hi> 'em. But as he has had ſo little ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in his endeavours to clear himſelf in the foregoing Particulars, ſo I ſomething wonder that he ſhould, with all this aſſurance, pretend that I have in all the other Inſtances groundleſly charg'd him with falſhood or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes. What! will his Lordſhip ſtill go about to perſwade us,<note place="margin">Diſc. <hi>p.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>That we have no other way of praiſing God, but by ſinging
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62574:21"/> a verſe or two of a Pſalm?</hi> Or that the <hi>firſt Principle</hi> he aſcribes to us about <hi>Prayer,</hi> is aſſerted in the <hi>Directory,</hi> when he himſelf tacitly corrects the miſtake in this <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Edition</hi> of his <hi>Diſcourſe?</hi> Or that he has truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented the Judgment and Senſe of the <hi>General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> in their <hi>Directions concerning Family Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</hi> p. 44, 45, Will he ſtill perſwade us, <hi>That a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Body of Diſſenters teach all Forms of Prayer to be unlawful,</hi> and <hi>affirm it ſinful to joyn where any are us'd?</hi> p. 57. Or, <hi>that on the account of this Principle, the pious cuſtom of Training up young People to a conſtant courſe of Devotion in their Morning and Evening ſecret Prayer, is too univerſally laid aſide among the Diſſenters;</hi> concerning the truth whereof, he confidently appeals to <hi>all of 'em?</hi> p. 64. Will he ſtill affirm, <hi>That the Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory excludes all Bodily Worſhip?</hi> p. 128. Or, <hi>That the Diſſenters in general do not ſtand up at their Thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, and generally ſit at their Publick Prayers?</hi> p. 129. And <hi>that they have not one viſible Act of Adoration in their Aſſemblies, except the Mens uncovering their Heads in Prayer?</hi> p. 130. Nay, will he ſtill perſiſt in it, <hi>That the Diſſenters are taught' that External Poſtures of Bodily Worſhip may in no caſe be practis'd?</hi> p. 137. <hi>That the Directory does not allow the People to ſignifie their Conſent by ſaying Amen to their Publick Thanksgivings?</hi> p. 138. <hi>That as to Gestures, ſuch as Kneeling, Standing, Bowing the Head, the Diſſenters condemn 'em all as Relicks of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry and Superſtition? That by turning all Bodily Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip out of their Aſſemblies, they are meer Spectators, not Joynt-worſhippers?</hi> p. 138, 139. Or, <hi>That neglecting to kneel at the Sacrament has hardned them against all Reverence in other parts of Worſhip?</hi> p. 144. And to add no more, Will he ſtill juſtifie all as true concerning the <hi>Diſſenters in general,</hi> which he has affirmed of 'em, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any diſtinction in reference to the <hi>Lord's Supper?</hi> p. 161, 162: Will the Biſhop ſtill think to perſwade us that in all theſe Matters of Fact he has <hi>justly</hi> accus'd us, and we have no reaſon to complain of being <hi>Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented</hi> and <hi>Abus'd?</hi> Does he think his bare word ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to bear down the Reputation of ſo conſiderable a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62574:21"/> Body of Proteſtants? Or would he have us ſilently bear the odium of ſo many grievous Reflections caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, which we are ſure of the <hi>injustice</hi> of, as we are that we know our own <hi>Opinions</hi> or <hi>Practices.</hi> His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip muſt therefore give us leave to be free with him on this occaſion, and to demand once more, That he either <hi>make good</hi> his Charge againſt us in theſe Particulars, or honeſtly confeſs his being <hi>mistaken</hi> or <hi>miſinform'd</hi> about 'em. Which if he would once do, he will find us very ready, not only to forgive the wrong done us, but to entertain more favourable thoughts of his veracity and charity, than 'tis almoſt poſſible for us to do, while theſe <hi>mistakes</hi> in his <hi>Book</hi> and in his <hi>Admonition,</hi> ſtand <hi>unretracted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are but Two things more which I think my ſelf oblig'd to take notice of, before I come to conſider the Exceptions he produces againſt ſome particular paſſages in the <hi>Remarks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is, That the Biſhop tells me, <q rend="inline">I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with him, and the Diſſenters of his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe; and blames me for interpoſing my ſelf without any Call or Reaſon, as well as Writing upon little or no Information.</q> 
               <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 158.</p>
            <p>To which I ſhall only offer a few Things in my own defence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I have already had occaſion to ſhew, That the Biſhop's <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> was in all juſt conſtruction levell'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Diſſenters in general. Nay, he uſually falls upon the <hi>Directory.</hi> which is a Book the generality of Diſſenters have a great and juſt value for, (the Compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of it having us'd great modeſty and tenderneſs in its Compoſure, without following the impoſing temper of thoſe that requir'd ſo peremptory a Declaration of Aſſent and Conſent to all things contain'd in and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd by the Book of Common Prayer, and the Form of Ordaining Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons) So that ſince his Diſcourſe is directed againſt what himſelf ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to be the common Opinions and Practices of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, every Man among 'em had a juſt right to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Common Cauſe, and the Biſhop has no juſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62574:22"/> ground to complain of any ones interpoſing in it Nay,</p>
            <p n="2">2. I had a very juſt Call to it; and that from the Diſſenting Miniſters of his own Dioceſe; who urg'd this Reaſon for it: That as the Biſhop's <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> might poſſeſs thoſe that were ſtrangers to the Diſſenters, with ill apprehenſions of 'em, if his Miſtakes were not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd; ſo few would read an Anſwer to it, if it came not out while the Matter was freſh in their minds; and they had leſs of leiſure for ſuch an undertaking at that time. And as I did not interpoſe without their deſire, ſo neither did I write without particular Informations from 'em, to which I have exactly adher'd, and from which I have yet ſeen no reaſon to recede.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I had yet a more particular concern in the Biſhop's Book; for tho' he would not vouchſafe an Anſwer to ſome former Papers of mine (ſhewing the unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of his excluding us from the Catholick Church) yet he took the liberty to miſrepreſent the <hi>Principles</hi> laid down in 'em, and charg'd em as <hi>inconſistent with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace of the Church.</hi> So that I lay under a <hi>particular</hi> obligation to vindicate my <hi>Self,</hi> as well as under a <hi>common</hi> one to juſtifie the <hi>common</hi> Opinions and Practices of Diſſenters, which the <hi>Biſhop</hi> had either miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented or argued againſt upon weak and inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent grounds.</p>
            <p>The ſecond the Biſhop complains of, is, <hi>That I give him hard words, and ſpeak hard things of him.</hi> Admon. p. 141, 142, 145, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I may, I think, in this Matter appeal to any equal Judges of things, Whether the Diſſenters have not juſter reaſon to complain of him, for ſaying ſo many <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>reproachful</hi> things of them without any juſt ground, than he to complain of me, only for telling him how greatly he has wrong'd us, and how little regard he has had to Truth in ſuch a multitude of Particulars wherein he has unreaſonably accuſed us. And indeed ſome of thoſe Accuſations tended ſo apparently to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame and render us odious, that it would have look'd like a tacit confeſſion of Guilt, to have expres'd no
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62574:22"/> diſtaſt at ſuch diſingenuous Treament. Nor do I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that the Biſhop had any great reaſon to expect the ſame deference to be paid to him, that would have been due to any other of his character, that had given any evidence of his Moderation and Charity. 'Tis true indeed, both his <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> and <hi>Admonition</hi> (bating the many ſevere, but groundleſs Aſperſions in 'em) have an air of <hi>mildneſs</hi> and <hi>temper</hi> in the ſtyle of 'em, and we often meet with <hi>friendly Appellations</hi> in 'em. But I take mens declared <hi>Opinions,</hi> and eſpecially their <hi>Actions,</hi> to be a ſurer Indication of their <hi>Temper</hi> than the common <hi>Civilities</hi> that occur in their way of writing. <hi>Joab</hi> had very obliging Language towards <hi>Amaſa</hi> in his mouth, <hi>Art thou in health my Brother?</hi> but he carried a ſharp <hi>Tool</hi> in his hand, and he had no <hi>friendly</hi> deſign. We can lay little ſtreſs on any ſeeming expreſſions of a man's <hi>charity,</hi> who will not recall that virtual Sentence of <hi>Damnation</hi> he has publickly paſt upon us, by <hi>denying us to be a part of the Catholick Church.</hi> We like not the gentle language of Writs <hi>de Excom. Cap.</hi> And we can perceive no extraordinary mildneſs and friendſhip in ſuch <hi>Covenants</hi> inſerted in <hi>Leaſes,</hi> as the following one: <q rend="inline">[And the ſaid <hi>A. B.</hi> his Executors, &amp;c. does by theſe Preſents covenant to and with the ſaid <hi>William</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Derry</hi> and his Succeſſors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the time being, that neither he the ſaid <hi>A. B.</hi> his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor any of 'em, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall or will Set, Let, or Demiſe the Premiſes, or any part thereof, to any Maſs or Popiſh Prieſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or to any Miniſter or Teacher diſſenting from the Church of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall wittingly or willingly ſuffer 'em to dwell or reſide on any part, parcel or member thereof, but him or them ſhall endeavour to expel and keep from the ſame, ſo far as by the Laws of this Realm they ſhall be enabled.]</q> So that if the Biſhop have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd ſomewhat <hi>ſharply</hi> for his <hi>unfair Dealing</hi> in this new Diſpute, he has but furniſh'd us with too juſt an Apology for it. And yet I know of no words given him ſo <hi>hard</hi> (how <hi>deſerved</hi> ſoever) as thoſe he has given the whole Body of Diſſenters which have been wholly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62574:23"/> 
               <hi>undeſerved.</hi> And I am ſure he will not find in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks</hi> any ſuch uncharitable Sentiments expreſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>eſtabliſht Church,</hi> as occur frequently in his <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> concerning the <hi>Diſſenters.</hi> And for what Touches himſelf only, he ſeems to have little reaſon of complaint, unleſs he can clear himſelf a little better in Matters of Fact than he has done in this <hi>Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to conſider the Biſhops few <hi>Exceptions</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Argumentative</hi> part of the <hi>Remarks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his Entrance on which he alledges, <hi>That 'tis the deſign of the Remarks to hinder the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters from joyning with the eſtabliſht Church in their ordinary Lord's-Day Worſhip.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Admon. p, 159.</note> Now I know no reaſon why his Lordſhip ſhould pretend that to be my deſign, which I no where propos'd as ſuch: For all I profeſt to attempt was, <hi>the Vindication of our own worſhip from the weak charge of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Inventions, and the retorting his Arguments, where they were ſtronger againſt the Worſhip of the eſtabliſht Church than againſt ours.</hi> But if the Biſhop here ſpeak of occaſional Communion with the eſtabliſht Church in her ordinary Lord's-Days Worſhip, 'tis ſtrange that he ſhould ſuppoſe it my deſign to hinder the Diſſenters from it, when I expreſly declare my own opinion for the lawfulneſs of it, <hi>Remarks</hi> p. 146. and urg'd him to expreſs the ſame Charity towards us, which I perceive he cannot be ſo eaſily perſwaded to.</p>
            <p>He farther premiſes, <q rend="inline">That it was incumbent on one that anſwer'd his Book, to juſtifie our way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, by ſhewing that the manner of performing it, in the ſeveral parts of it, as diſtinguiſh't from theirs, is warranted by Scripture Precept or Preſident, or by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect conſequence from thence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But (he ſaith) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of undertaking this Task, Mr. <hi>B.</hi> argues againſt and condemns the Rule; whereas, as ſtrict as it appears, he has juſtified all the particular ways of Worſhip in the <hi>eſtabliſht Church</hi> by it; and if I could have done the ſame for ours, I need not have declin'd it.</q> 
               <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 159, 160.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:62574:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If his Lordſhip had anſwer'd the <hi>Remarks,</hi> he would have had perhaps ſome pretence to have ſaid this. But he has none now, when he himſelf is forc'd (as I ſhall ſhew) to alter his own Rule, when I had ſo largely prov'd that our Worſhip, in moſt particular parts of it, was more agreeable to Scripture-Precept or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample than theirs; and alſo ſhewn him that his Rule, as laid down by himſelf, would condemn all Churches in the World in which there were ſome circumſtantial modes, and thoſe very lawful, that neither expreſs Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <hi>Precept</hi> nor <hi>Pattern</hi> could be produc'd for, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed could reaſonably be expected. And therefore ſince the Biſhop lays ſo great ſtreſs on this Matter, I ſhall carefully examine the Three Heads he ſuggeſts in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He ſaith, <hi>I give another Rule for the ordering God's Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſaith, <hi>I endeavour to perſwade the Diſſenters that the greateſt Exception they have against joyning with the establiſht Church is not matter of Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſaith, <hi>I alledge that he has omitted to handle that part of Worſhip against which the Diſſenters have the greatest Exception, and that becauſe he could not defend it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. He ſaith, <hi>I give another Rule for the ordering God's Service.</hi> And to that purpoſe he thus pretends to cite my own Expreſſions. <q rend="inline">As to his new Rule of Worſhip, you will find it in <hi>p.</hi> 7. in theſe words. Modes and Circumſtances of Divine Worſhip, —tho' neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in general by Divine Precept, yet are left in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to be determin'd by Human Prudence. For tho' God has commanded Publick Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet what time or place we ſhall aſſemble in, in what or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe parts of Worſhip ſhall be perform'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are left to Human Determination, only therein the general Rules of Scripture muſt be regarded. <hi>From whence his Lordſhip concludes,</hi> That 'tis my Rule or Principle. That all Modes of Worſhip whatever are left to Human Prudence, and particularly the determination of Time, Place, Order, Circumſtances, Poſtures, and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſils
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62574:24"/> in all Caſes. <hi>Against which he argues,</hi> That God has not only given us general Rules to praiſe him, pray to him, hear his Word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but he has likewiſe given us many particular Rules and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples concerning each of theſe, to which if we dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently attend, and mind the conſequences of 'em, and apply 'em to the like caſes, we may have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Directions from Scripture to order our Worſhip, without having recourſe to Human Prudence.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the Biſhop pleaſe to review the <hi>Marks,</hi> he will find that he has plainly miſtaken and miſrepreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what they aſſert in reference to this matter, that he might have ſome pretence to find fault with it. For in the place he cites I am laying down no <hi>Rule</hi> at all, but only mentioning an improper ſenſe of Human In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, as the Reader would have evidently perceiv'd if the Biſhop had not, by miſ-citing my words, maim'd 'em, and perverted the plain ſenſe of 'em: For they run thus in the <hi>Remarks,</hi> p. 7. <q rend="inline">It remains only that I ſubjoyn, in order to the clearing the ſtate of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, That there is a very improper ſenſe, in which this phraſe of Human Inventions in the Worſhip of God may poſſibly be us'd, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſignifie ſuch Modes and Circumſtances of Divine Worſhip, as tho' neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in general by Divine Precept, yet are left in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to be determin'd by Human Prudence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Of which kind of Circumſtantial Modes, I there produce ſeveral Inſtances relating to Time, Place, Orders, U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and would gladly know whether his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip can produce any particular Determination of 'em in Scripture for every particular <hi>Church, viz.</hi> What time of the Lord's-Day their Publick Worſhip ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, what Place they ſhall aſſemble in, what Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Bible they ſhall uſe; whether they ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with Prayer or Praiſe, or what Veſſels they ſhall uſe in the Celebration of the Sacraments. But I do by no means ſuppoſe, <q rend="inline">That God has given no particular Directions at all in reference to the Modes of Worſhip, <hi>but the quite contrary; for 'tis one Instance I produce of</hi> Human Inventions.</q> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 55. <q rend="inline">That whereas every part
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62574:24"/> of Worſhip enjoyn'd by God as Prayer, Praiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is capable of being perform'd in various Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Modes, if the Law of God expreſly enjoyn us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular Mode, than to deviſe another of our own, excluſive of that which he has choſen and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd, is to bring in a ſinful Human Invention in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Worſhip. As I inſtance there in Prayers in an unknown Tongue, Communicating without the Cup, Solitary Communions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Such Modes then as God has determin'd by the particular Directions of his Word, I plainly exclude from the Determination of Human Prudence. Nay, ſo far am I from ſuppoſing that Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Prudence may Arbitrarily appoint any Modes of Worſhip that Men think fit, that I rank among ſinful Inventions, <hi>p.</hi> 6. <q rend="inline">All ſuch Rites and Ceremonies of Mens own deviſing, as are no way warranted by any general Rules of Scripture, and yet made ſtated Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendages of any part of Divine Worſhip, and terms of Communion in it.</q> All therefore that I aſſert is, That all thoſe Circumſtantial Modes of Worſhip, that are in general neceſſary by Divine Precept (becauſe God's own Commands about his Worſhip cannot be executed without the determination of 'em) and yet are not in particular determin'd in Scripture, muſt be determin'd by Human Prudence; and that to call ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Modes, when determined agreeable to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rules of Scripture, <hi>Human Inventions,</hi> is a very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper ſenſe of the word, and to make 'em <hi>ſinful,</hi> is a Principle fit only for the wildeſt Sectaries ſince it would condemn a great many prudential orders practis'd both by them and us, and indeed by all <hi>Churches</hi> in the World. And if the Biſhop pretend to diſprove this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, he muſt produce us particular Precept or Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern from Scripture, for his beginning Publick Worſhip at nine or ten in the forenoon, rather than twelve, for his meeting at the Cathedral, rather then in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place; for his uſing the old Tranſlation of the Pſalms, and the new one of the reſt of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for his uſing at the Sacrament <hi>Loaves rather than Cakes,</hi> and uſing one ſort of Wine rather then another,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62574:25"/> and employing Peuter or Silver Veſſels rather than Wooden or Golden ones. So that what I aſſert, is not only very innocent, and free from any ſuch dangerous conſequences as the Biſhop ſuggeſts, but indeed too ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious and plain for any Man of ſenſe to doubt of it; and his Lordſhip could never have begun any new Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute about it, if he had not rais'd a miſt by miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſenſe of as clear Expreſſions as could well be us'd on this Subject. Since then he has ſo plainly miſtaken in aſcribing ſuch a <hi>Rule</hi> to me as I no where laid down, but have ſo fully diſclaim'd, all the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences he draws from it, either to his own Advantage, or our Prejudice, fall of courſe, and I am no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in 'em as conſequences drawn from any Opinion of mine: For 'tis plain, the Rules laid down in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks</hi> do not juſtifie all the Modes of Worſhip practis'd in the eſtabliſht Church, neither that way of ſinging the Proſe <hi>Pſalms</hi> that excludes the generality of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor the Cathedral Muſick, nor the confining all Publick Prayers to ſtinted Forms, nor reading the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocripha, nor bowing towards the Eaſt or Altar, or at the Name of Jeſus, nor Reading one part of the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers where many of the People cannot hear 'em, nor the uſe of the Croſs, or our ſort of Sponſors in Baptiſm, nor ſo much as kneeling in the Act of Receiving. Theſe and many more particular Modes are not defenſible by any <hi>Rule</hi> I have laid down, tho' I have ſhewn him that our own Practices are. Nay, no <hi>Rule</hi> I have laid down will defend all ſort of Holy-days, nor any Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions relating to Habits, Place or Utenſils that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Edification, or to Order and Decency.</p>
            <p>But whereas the Biſhop pretends, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Rules and Directions he had produc'd from Scripture,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adm.</hi> p. 43, 44.</note> relating to the ſeveral parts of Worſhip, <q rend="inline">The Letter of Scripture is clearly on his ſide, and I have not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd Scripture to Scripture, but have declin'd the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral ſenſe in many caſes without reaſon, and have preferr'd the determinations of Human Prudence in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as being more for Edification than the Scripture
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62574:25"/> Examples, and particularly in the ſinging of Pſalms.</q> I muſt needs on this occaſion acquaint him, that I think the quite contrary to what he Aſſerts, will appear to any that impartially compare the <hi>Remarks</hi> and his <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> together, at leaſt I hope his Lordſhip does not expect we ſhould take his peremptory Aſſertion for a proof of it: but ſince he ſuppoſes this Obſervation to be manifeſt in reference to that particular Mode of Praiſing God by <hi>ſinging of Pſalms,</hi> I ſhould add, that I think it not ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious in the Biſhop to Aſſert this with ſuch aſſurance, when I have in the <hi>Remarks</hi> taken ſuch particular pains to ſhew, That our ways of ſinging Pſalms is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the only Precept in Scripture, that relates to the uſe of 'em in our Praiſes, 5 <hi>Eph.</hi> 19. 3 <hi>Col.</hi> 16. to which he has yet vouchſaf'd no Anſwer. He has been told, <q rend="inline">That the Precept enjoyns vocal ſinging, which bare ſaying 'em no way Anſwers, <hi>p.</hi> 13, 14. That ſince the Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> were wrote in ſuch ſort of Metre and Verſe as was then us'd, and ſince the knowledge of their Muſical Tunes and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is quite loſt, to ſuppoſe us oblig'd to an exact imitation of 'em, were to ſuppoſe us oblig'd to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities. That therefore the Command which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges Chriſtian Churches to <hi>ſing Pſalms,</hi> neceſſarily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us to turn 'em into ſuch ſort of <hi>Metre</hi> and <hi>Verſe,</hi> as will beſt accommodate 'em to be <hi>ſung</hi> by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Whereas to put 'em into no other <hi>Metre</hi> than the pointed <hi>Pſalter</hi> in the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the generality of the People from any capacity of complying with God's own Command for <hi>ſinging</hi> 'em. And as the <hi>Tunes</hi> of thoſe pointed <hi>Pſalms</hi> are quite different from <hi>Hebrew</hi> ones, ſo they are as much a <hi>Human Invention</hi> as the <hi>Tunes</hi> of the Common <hi>Metro-Verſions,</hi> and therefore do ſet up that pointed <hi>Pſalter</hi> in the <hi>Service-Book,</hi> whoſe Tunes the Body of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cannot follow to the Excluſion of thoſe <hi>Metre-Verſions</hi> according to which they can joyn in ſinging Pſalms, (as the Biſhop ſeems to deſign) is in his lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to ſet up an <hi>Human Invention</hi> to the violation of a <hi>Divine Command,</hi> by rendring the Peoples obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62574:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:62574:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:62574:27"/> of it impracticable,</q> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 189, 190. And ſhould not his Lordſhip in all equity and reaſon have attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a clear refutation of this Argument, before he had ventur'd to ſay, <hi>That in this particular of ſinging Pſalms, the Scripture is on his ſide, and that I prefer the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Human Prudence before Scripture Examples;</hi> when I have ſo plainly ſhewn him, That the <hi>Example</hi> or <hi>Pattern</hi> of Jewiſh ſinging is unimitable by us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe unknown to us, but that the <hi>Precepts</hi> of Scripture plainly obliges us to this way of ſinging, becauſe 'tis moſt generally practicable among us. To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is it to reaſon in theſe matters, if the Biſhop think his bare <hi>Affirmation</hi> ſufficient to weigh down all <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi> And why does he call this <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 164. <hi>Our manner of ſinging Pſalms,</hi> when 'tis <hi>theirs</hi> as well as <hi>ours;</hi> and tho' he has ventur'd to exclude it from being any ſubſtantial part of their Worſhip, and made it a meer Diverſion, yet he has done it without any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or Commiſſion from the eſtabliſht Church, by whom it ſeems allow'd as a ſtated part of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>And as the Biſhop has aſcrib'd to me a <hi>Rule</hi> about Worſhip that I never laid down, ſo he ſtiffly pretends to adhere to his <hi>own,</hi> when yet what I had alledg'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, as unhappily worded by himſelf, has ſo far convinc'd him, that he found himſelf neceſſitated to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large it. He had before ſaid, <hi>That all ways of Worſhip are diſpleaſing to God that are not expreſly contain'd in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſc. <hi>p.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>or warranted by Examples of Holy Men men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd therein.</hi> He had us'd the phraſe, <hi>ways of Worſhip,</hi> frequently to ſignifie circumſtantial <hi>Modes</hi> of it. I had told him, That if his words be taken in this ſtrict ſenſe, they contain ſuch an Aſſertion, that if a man believ'd it, he would find it hard to joyn in any Aſſembly in the Chriſtian World, and muſt renounce Communion with the Pariſh Churches. (For many circumſtantial <hi>Modes</hi> of Worſhip are practis'd there, which are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſly contain'd in the Scriptures, nor warranted by any Examples of Holy Men that have us'd thoſe particular circumſtantial Modes, <hi>ex. gr.</hi> The ſinging
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62574:27"/> Pſalms as appointed in the Common-Prayer-Book, or in the Metre compos'd by <hi>Sternhold</hi> and <hi>Hopkins,</hi> the uſe of a ſtinted Liturgy in general, and particularly our Engliſh one, Reading the Apocrypha, bowing at the Name of Jeſus, kneeling at the Sacrament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) But his Lordſhip, inſtead of taking any notice of this obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt his Rule, very ſilently now extends it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 165.</note> only to make thoſe things unlawful <hi>that are not contain'd in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or warranted by Example of Holy Men in it, or may not be deduc'd by clear conſequence, or parity of Reaſon from them.</hi> Now 'tis evident that many things may be drawn by <hi>clear conſequence</hi> and <hi>parity of reaſon</hi> from the <hi>Precepts</hi> of Scripture that are not <hi>expreſly contain'd</hi> in 'em. And the ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Scripture Examples.</hi> So that the Biſhop has now really charg'd his <hi>Rule</hi> by this new comprehenſive Addition to it, and as 'tis now laid down, 'tis much the ſame with what I have aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, tho' I think not ſo clear. And now he will find, there's nothing in our Worſhip but what is eaſily juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable by his own <hi>Rule</hi> in this juſt latitude: For our manner of <hi>ſinging</hi> it ſelf, (which is the Inſtance he ſo often inſiſts on) may be drawn by juſt conſequence and by parity of reaſon, both from the <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> of <hi>ſinging</hi> in the Holy Scriptures. For if we muſt ſing Pſalms, and that in a way moſt conducive to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Edification, we muſt uſe ſuch Metre and Tunes as the People can joyn in: And if the Jews us'd ſuch ſort of Metre and Tunes as were moſt known and common among them, we may by parity of reaſon chooſe thoſe that are moſt familiar to us. And now I hope the Biſhop will, upon the review, ſee how little reaſon he had to except againſt this part of the <hi>Remarks,</hi> when they have really oblig'd him to reform and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his own <hi>Rule,</hi> and bring it up to that I had laid down, tho' to conceal the matter, he has thought fit to miſunderſtand and pervert mine, or rather to coyn a new one for me.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Biſhop alledges, <hi>That I endeavour to perſwade the Diſſenters of his Dioceſe, that the greateſt Exception
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62574:28"/> againſt joyning with the eſtabliſht Church, is not the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their Publick ordinary Worſhip.</hi> On which he makes ſeveral Obſervations.</p>
            <p>Before I conſider 'em, I muſt premiſe that 'tis true, I have told his Lordſhip that the Conteſt between the <hi>eſtabliſht Church</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> does not lye chiefly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their ordinary Lord's-Day Worſhip, but what oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs in other <hi>Offices,</hi> and chiefly about the corruptions and abuſes of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and 'tis no more than has been frequently ſuggeſted by the moſt judicious N.C. Divines that have wrote on the Subject of our Differences. But why does he pretend that I diſwade any Diſſenters from joyning with the eſtabliſht Church (if he mean it concerning all <hi>occaſional Communion</hi> with 'em) when I have ſo expreſly declar'd my Judgment for it, and in vain urg'd him to the like declaration of his Charity towards us, and never pretend to alledge our Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in Reference to Worſhip or Diſcipline, as any Argument againſt ſuch <hi>occaſional Communion</hi> in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Lord's-Day Service. There is no reaſon then to pervert what I have offer'd to ſuch an uncharitable purpoſe, ſo that his following Obſervations are found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on a miſtaken ſuppoſition. And therefore I ſhall content my ſelf with theſe ſhort Remarks on 'em.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I did then, and do ſtill think it requiſite to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Reader, that the Biſhop had not in this <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> ſo much as touch'd the Principal Matters in Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the <hi>eſtabliſht Church</hi> and the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> and particularly thoſe to which this charge of <hi>Human Inventions</hi> does moſt properly belong. And whereas be now tells us, that if he writ about <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> we ſhould be leſs pleas'd with his perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adm.</hi> p. 165, 166.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he muſt look on the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Frame of our whole Conſtitution as a meer Human Creature,</hi> &amp;c. I muſt ſo far agree with him. That if he treat that Subject in the ſame manner that he has done this about <hi>Worſhip,</hi> we ſhall certainly be leſs pleas'd with it, becauſe all thoſe faults that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in the manner of handling this Subject, will be the more aggrevated if he repeat 'em on another.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:62574:28"/>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas the Biſhop pretends, I <hi>deſire to ſhift ground, and thence preſumes I apprehend ſome diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in it.</hi> I do not find he has any reaſon for ſuch a Triumph for my having avoided the conſideration of any thing in his Book that carried the face of an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Nor have I any need to multiply Matters of Controverſie from any Anſwer that his Lordſhip has yet given to the <hi>Remarks.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 46.</note> And whereas he ſaith, <q rend="inline">That I attempt not to juſtifie their ſitting at Prayers, nor their omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to add their <hi>Amen</hi> to their Prayers, nor the manner and frequency of their Communion, nor their way of ſinging Pſalms;</q> 
               <hi>I ſhall only add,</hi> That for ſitting at Publick Prayer, I was no more oblig'd to defend any particular perſons in that <hi>poſture</hi> that indulge it out of ſloth, than he to defend the <hi>Toying</hi> or <hi>Laughing,</hi> that's too often us'd in their Churches: But his Lordſhip was oblig'd, either to defend his charging this upon our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, as if we taught, <hi>That no poſtures of Reverence may be lawfully us'd;</hi> and <hi>condemn'd ſuch as ſtanding and kneeling as Relicks of Idolatry;</hi> or elſe to retract ſo <hi>hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Calumnies</hi> as theſe muſt be, if they are untrue and groundleſs. For <hi>adding Amen,</hi> I ſhall, if that will pleaſe the Biſhop, concur with him that 'tis more agreeable to Scripture Pattern, that the People pronounce it more audibly; but I hope this omiſſion ſignifies nothing to his Charge of <hi>Human Inventions.</hi> For the Matter of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating the Lord's-Supper, if it refer to the <hi>poſture,</hi> I hope the Biſhop is convinc'd, that <hi>ours</hi> is more agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Scripture Pattern. For the <hi>frequency</hi> of it, I hope hee'l allow the generality of the Diſſenters have much the advantage above the generality of the <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> by communicating much oftner. And for what concerns the Practice of the Diſſenters in his Dioceſe, it has been already conſider'd in the Account of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact, and I have there ſhown that their way of Adminiſtring it once a year, is equivalent to its being Adminiſtred thrice in the Pariſh Churches, as to the frequency of their Members Communicating. And for <hi>ſinging Pſalms,</hi> I have already ſaid enough to ſhew
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62574:29"/> him that our Practice needs no <hi>Reformation,</hi> but rather his unreaſonable prejudices againſt this part of Divine Worſhip, common both to them and us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Biſhop need take no pains to prove, <hi>That my demands about the Reformation of the Diſcipline of the establiſht Church, are not Arguments againſt all occaſional Communion with 'em.</hi> For they were never propo'd for that end; but then I muſt tell him, That where there are in a Kingdom two Parties, or Bodies of Proteſtants, in one of whom both the <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of Chriſt is more fully reſtor'd to its primitive ſimplicity and purity, in the other there are ſome defects and corruptions left in their <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> almoſt entirely neglected or perverted and abus'd. I think every conſiderate Chriſtian ſhould prefer the ſtated Communion of that Party, in which neceſſary Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation has made a happier progreſs, and thoſe better Reformed Churches, have no reaſon to ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to thoſe corruptions they have rejected. And moderate and wiſe men will ſeparate from the Churches of neither Party, as if they were no true Churches, and no part of the Church Catholick, but will rather to ſhew their regard to <hi>Truth,</hi> more ſtatedly communicate with thoſe on whoſe ſide it lies in the Matters in Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and yet to expreſs their <hi>Charity,</hi> maintain oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional Communion with the other, ſo far as they can do it without Practiſing what themſelves think unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whereas the Biſhop is ſo much diſpleaſed with thoſe <hi>Requests</hi> that I have offer'd to the Conforming Clergy, relating to thoſe Practices wherein we chiefly deſire ſome Reformation of their preſent Diſcipline, and thinks me very unreaſonable in propoſing 'em, and cannot ſee to what good purpoſe they can ſerve; I ſhall, to give him all the ſatisfaction I can, acquaint him with the true Reaſons of my offering 'em.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I take the Abuſes, of which ſome Reformation is there requeſted, to be the chief Obſtacles to that happy Union among us, which has been ſo long the earneſt deſire of all good men, and I hope I can moſt ſincerely
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62574:29"/> ſay my own. So that I think none who have that end in their Eye, can be reaſonably blamed for humbly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to Publick Conſideration ſo proper and effectual means to attain it; from which I thought his Lordſhip's <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> had ſome tendency to divert the minds of men by amuſing 'em with a new Diſpute of <hi>Human Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> And therefore I thought this a very ſutable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to lay open the main grounds of our unhappy Differences, that if any charitable Perſons ſhould think of any attempts to compoſe them, they might by a true view of the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> judge of the <hi>Remedy</hi> proper to heal it. And truly, 'till theſe Corruptions be reform'd, I ſee as yet little reaſon to hope for any <hi>concord</hi> in our <hi>practice,</hi> tho' I would hope to ſee much greater in our mutual <hi>Affections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I take theſe to be <hi>abuſes,</hi> which the generality of the moſt judicious and learned, as well as ſober and charitable of the Conforming Clergy and Laity are ſenſible of, and would readily concur in their deſires and endeavours to reform, if they had a fair opportunity for it, ſo that I did not believe theſe <hi>Requests</hi> would be any matter of juſt <hi>offence</hi> to them, nor do I yet find that they are. And for the <hi>offence</hi> of any that would perpetuate our Diviſions, by keeping up thoſe Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are the chief Engine of 'em, becauſe they are ſerviceable to their Secular Intereſt, I think not my ſelf much oblig'd to regard it. The Glory of God, and Concord of Chriſtians are ſo much more valuable an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, that we may juſtly purſue it, tho' it ſhould claſh with the Humours, the Ambition or Avarice of Men, to which too many even of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> have too long Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crific'd the more precious Concernments both of the Churches <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two things indeed which the Biſhop Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thoſe Requeſts, of which I am concern'd to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That ſome of 'em are founded on most unjust Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of their Practices and Principles, which if truly Repreſented needs no Reformation, as may appear</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>from his adding to,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Admon. <hi>p.</hi> 171.</note> 
               <hi>and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62574:30"/> taking from our third and fourth Canons,</hi> p. 179. <hi>And may farther appear in the</hi> 2d, 3d, 4th, 7th, 8th, 11th, 12th, <hi>and</hi> 13th <hi>Requests.</hi> Now I have review'd all theſe, and can ſee no ſuch <hi>unjuct Repreſentations</hi> in 'em. So that I think, his Lordſhip had been more juſt, if he had, either never advanc'd this Charge againſt me, or had taken the pains to prove it. Particularly, I cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, wherein I have added to theſe two Canons, in what I have cited of 'em, or why I muſt be ſaid to take from 'em, becauſe I only cite that part of 'em, which my <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> there led me to take notice of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is pleas'd to inſinuate, <hi>That I give ill Language in thoſe Requests;</hi> and to that purpoſe faith, <hi>That I expoſe the Kingdom and Protestant Inhabitants of it, as again, overſpread with Swearing, Profanation of the Lord's-Day, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Pride, Luxury,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>An Imputation</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which I can by no means allow to be general; there being, I am perſwaded by the goodneſs of God, a manifest abatement of theſe in this Dioceſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhould be glad to hear of ſuch an Abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe Sins in his <hi>Dioceſe,</hi> and doubt not if true, that the Diſſenting Miniſters have been no way negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to contribute towards it. But if the Biſhop deny the Truth of this Complaint, concerning the generality of the Proteſtants of this Kingdom, as 'tis there deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, he ſees with other eyes, than any ſober Perſon I have yet convers'd with. For <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Profanation</hi> of the Lord's-Day, no good Man can converſe in any part of the Kingdom, without being a ſorrowful Ear and Eye-witneſs of it. Nor does there appear any conſiderable abatement of thoſe other Crimes, from what was before, beſides what the diminution of mens Eſtates have neceſſitated them to. So that I cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine what <hi>ill Language</hi> it ſhould be, to mention and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the revival of theſe Vices, and requeſt all Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to concur in their endeavours, to preſerve or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim thoſe under their care from 'em. And I fear that the generality of Proteſtants among us, need the loudeſt call we can give 'em to <hi>Repentance,</hi> inſtead of ſuch an undeſerved Commendation as tends to perſwade 'em,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62574:30"/> there is not ſo great and general a neceſſity of it. The common guilt is too great and too deeply aggravated, to be either conceal'd or extenuated, and deſerves a fuller Deſcription and a ſeverer Reproof then I had then occaſion for.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The third Allegation which the Biſhop ſaith, I uſe to take off the force of his Book, is, <hi>That he hath omitted to handle that part of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the establiſht Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Admon. p. 54.</note> 
               <hi>against which the Diſſenters have the greatest Exception, and particularly what refers to Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I felt no ſuch force in his Book, as needed this new Diſpute to take it off. But 'tis true enough, That the Debate about <hi>Human Inventions</hi> does more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly concern <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> than the other parts of Worſhip his Lordſhip had inſiſted on.</p>
            <p>And therefore, ſince the Biſhop has offer'd us ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing new on this Subject, I ſhall the more willingly addreſs my ſelf to the Examination of it, becauſe the precedent part of the Admonition, has left the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between us almoſt wholly untouch'd, and contains little but ſuch ſlight Cavils about it, as were in effect obviated in the <hi>Remarks</hi> themſelves. And here</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Biſhop gives us the Reaſon why he omitted this part of Worſhip, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. "Becauſe it was occaſional,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 172, 173.</note> not ordinary.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Anſw.</hi> But he knew that in a Diſcourſe about the <hi>Inventions of Men in the Worſhip of God,</hi> it was proper to conſider that part of Worſhip about which that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute chiefly lay.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <q rend="inline">Becauſe he found the Defects and Additions of our Directory ſo great in this Office, that they deſerv'd a Diſcourſe by themſelves.</q>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 173, 174.</note> And accordingly he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions theſe following <hi>Defects</hi> in the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p n="1">1. There is no expreſs Covenant order'd in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory, to be made in the name of the Child Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd, either by the Parent or any elſe, tho' there be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62574:31"/> no other way of engaging a Child that cannot Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is no Profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Directory from any Parent or Offerer of any Child.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is no ſolemn Recognition of the Vow of Baptiſm required from Perſons Baptiz'd in their Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, when they come to underſtand their Duty. As it is in Confirmation with us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The expreſs words of the Covenant, are not preſcribed out of the Word of God, but is left to the Diſcretion of every Miniſter, to impoſe what he will on the Baptiz'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I know no great harm to the Cauſe of <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> if we ſhould own there are ſome Omiſſions in the Directory; eſpecially when the Compilers, to avoid the rigorous and impoſing humour, that had too long reign'd in others, ſeem to have left many things to the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of particular Paſtors, which they would not poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively enjoyn. And for theſe Defects which the Biſhop has cited out of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Treatiſe of Infant Baptiſm,</hi> they are not ſo material as his Lordſhip ſeems to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, and are eaſily ſupplyed by every Miniſter that thinks more expreſs Profeſſions requiſite than are there poſitively enjoyn'd.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>firſt, The making of an Expreſs Covenant in the name of the Child,</hi> if the Biſhop mean by it, that the Parent ſhould explicitly profeſs his Dedicating his Child to God, and bringing it thereby under a Solemn Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to the Duties of his Covenant, this is really inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in that Profeſſion he is required by the <hi>Directory</hi> to make of his <hi>deſire to have it Baptiz'd:</hi> and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly 'tis uſual for the Miniſters to propoſe the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more fully to this purpoſe; <hi>Do you profeſs your deſire of having this Child dedicated by Baptiſm to the Faith, Worſhip and Service of God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost?</hi> But if he mean that the <hi>Parent</hi> or <hi>Offerer</hi> of the Child ſhould make ſuch a Profeſſion in the Child's name, as our <hi>Sponſors</hi> are order'd to do in the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> 'tis ſo far from being a <hi>Defect</hi> in our <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:62574:31"/> that it enjoyns no ſuch thing, that 'tis no ſmall <hi>Blemiſh</hi> of the Office of Baptiſm in the <hi>Service-Book,</hi> that it requires ſuch a Profeſſion from 'em, as <hi>perſonating</hi> the Child they preſent. And that his Lordſhip may be aſſured Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> intended no ſuch <hi>Expreſs Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting in the name of the Child</hi> as this is, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce his own words (and the rather becauſe I take them to carry great weight and force in 'em) in his <hi>N. Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſtated,</hi> &amp;c. he brings in the <hi>Lawyer</hi> asking, <q rend="inline">What is your fourth <hi>Objection</hi> againſt our way of <hi>Baptiſm?</hi> To which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> thus <hi>Anſwers:</hi> That in perſonating the Child, they ſay, that they (and ſo he by them) doth at preſent believe, renounce and deſire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> falſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating that Infants are at preſent bound to do this by another. And yet the ſame Men plead that God doth not accept him for the Faith of his Parents, when as God requireth no Faith or Repentance of Infants, but only that they be the Seed of Penitent Believers devoted to Chriſt. And in the Catechiſm 'tis ſaid, that <hi>(Repentance and Faith are requir'd of Perſons to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd; and that Infants who cannot perform theſe, are Baptiz'd becauſe they promiſe 'em by their Sureties, which Promiſe when they come to Age, themſelves are bound to perform.)</hi> Where note, that the former <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> had <hi>[They perform 'em by their Sureties]</hi> They perceiv'd that having ſaid Faith and Repentance are requiſite, Infants they ſaw muſt have at preſent what is requiſite at preſent. And they knew that they had them not themſelves, and ſo were fain to hold that the Sureties Faith and Repentance was theirs, and a performance of that requir'd Condition. But the Makers of the new Book ſaw that this would not hold, and ſo they ſay, "[Tho' Faith and Repentance be requir'd of Perſons to be Baptiz'd, yet Infants are Baptiz'd becauſe they promiſe 'em by their Sureties to be hereafter perform'd,] amending the former <hi>Errour</hi> by a greater or a <hi>double</hi> one: 1. Granting Faith and Repentance are pre-requiſite, and yet confeſſing that Infants have neither of their <hi>own</hi> or <hi>Sureties</hi> for 'em, and yet are to be <hi>Baptiz'd.</hi> 2. Or making a Promiſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62574:32"/> Future Faith and Repentance to be Preſent Faith and Repentance. 3. Or tho' Faith and Repentance be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in thoſe that are to be Baptiz'd, yet God will at preſent juſtifie and ſave all that have it not in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, becauſe they promiſe it hereafter. All plain Contradictions; as if they ſaid, 'Tis requiſite in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be Baptiz'd, and 'tis not requiſite. L—How would you have 'em have anſwer'd theſe? M. Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Faith and Repentance are requiſite in adult Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be Baptiz'd; and in Infants, that they be the Seed of the Faithful, devoted by them to God in Chriſt, according to his offer'd Covenant of Grace.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far that accurate Divine, from whom his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip may learn, That the modeſty of the Compilers of the <hi>Directory,</hi> which made their Orders about this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſeem defective by leaving ſome Particulars to the prudence and liberty of particular Miniſters, is far more excuſable, than the aſſurance of thoſe who impoſe in ſuch ſolemn Profeſſions, things ſo confus'd and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent. If there be any defect in their <hi>Orders,</hi> 'tis eaſily ſupplied; but the miſtakes of the <hi>Service-Book</hi> are remedileſly impos'd on all that Adminiſter this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance according to it.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>ſecond</hi> Defect, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">That there is in the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory</hi> no Profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith requir'd from the Parent or Offerer of any Child;</q> I think there is ſuch a virtual Profeſſion requir'd by the <hi>Directory,</hi> when it enjoyns the Miniſter to require from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, a ſolemn Promiſe to bring up his Child <hi>in the knowledge of the Grounds of the Chriſtian Religion, and in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord.</hi> For this implys his owning himſelf the Chriſtian Religion; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that his being a known <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of it, is preſuppos'd to his Childrens Admiſſion to that Ordinance. Nor does the <hi>Directory</hi> hinder the Miniſter from requiring a more expreſs Profeſſion from the Parent, of the Chriſtian Faith, where it is doubtful whether he own it or no. And I am ſure the Form of Baptiſm drawn up by the N. C. Divines at the <hi>Savoy-Conference,</hi> in their Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals for Accommodation, does expreſly require it; and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62574:32"/> I have obſerv'd it ordinarily requir'd, at leaſt in general terms.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>third</hi> and <hi>fourth</hi> Defects of the <hi>Directory,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">That there is no ſolemn Recognition of the Vow of Baptiſm requir'd of Perſons Baptiz'd in Infancy, when they come to underſtand their Duty, as there is in the Confirmation practis'd in the eſtabliſht Church; and that the expreſs words of the Covenant are not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed out of the Word of God.</q> Tho' I take this to be an Omiſſion, and therefore have both my ſelf practis'd, and known many others practiſe that <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> recommended in the <hi>Reformed Liturgy,</hi> drawn up by the N. C. Divines at the <hi>Savoy-Conference,</hi> (<q rend="inline">ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which no Perſon Baptiz'd is admitted to the Lord's Supper, till at years of diſcretion, not only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Baptiſmal Covenant, but with his own mouth, and with his own conſent openly before the Church, ratifie and confirm it, and promiſe his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obſervance of it to the end.</q> In which Liturgy there is alſo an excellent Form of the Baptiſmal Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, drawn up as agreeable to the Scripture as any I have yet ſeen) yet I think this Omiſſion of the <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory,</hi> far more excuſable than what the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> impoſes in reference to Confirmation, of which they have both made ſomething too like a Sacrament, and alſo turn'd a very uſeful practice, and agreeable to the general Rules of Scripture into a <hi>Childiſh Formality,</hi> as I had occaſion to ſhew in the <hi>Remarks.</hi> 'Tis eaſier to ſupply ſuch Defects, than to remove ſuch unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Head, with obſerving that the Biſhop has, of all Men, the leaſt reaſon to blame the <hi>Directory</hi> for theſe Defects: For unleſs he could produce expreſs Scriptural <hi>Precepts</hi> or <hi>Pattern</hi> for theſe things, which he ſaith the <hi>Directory</hi> has omitted, (as I think no Man can do it) he muſt, according to his former Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, cenſure 'em for <hi>Human Inventions,</hi> and rather commend the <hi>Directory</hi> for omitting them.</p>
            <p>For the Biſhop's Charge againſt the <hi>Directory,</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring Additional Conditions contrary to Scripture
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62574:33"/> Preſidents, of which he gives us only one Inſtance, viz. <hi>Its ordering that Baptiſm be not Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in private Places,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Admon. p. 174.</note> 
               <hi>but in the place of Publick Worſhip, and in the face of the Congregation.</hi> I ſuppoſe the Biſhop will grant that it ſhould ordinarily be Adminiſtred in Publick; and if theſe words of the <hi>Directory</hi> were intended in the ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſenſe they are capable of, I am ſure the generality of Diſſenters have receded from the rigour of this <hi>Rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The Biſhop comes to ſhew that my Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Croſs is of no force.</p>
            <p>Of this he only gives us this ſhort Account, <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 175. <hi>His great Objection against it is, That we make a new Human Sacrament, and then it must be a Human Invention.</hi> And upon this the Biſhop proceeds to give us a new Account of his own concerning the Nature of a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and endeavours to ſhew that the <hi>Croſs</hi> is not made a Sacrament by 'em, according to that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. Now tho' I ſhould have thought it fairer to have propos'd the Argument in the ſame manner I had done, yet in order to the bringing this Debate to ſome iſſue, I ſhall do theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall ſet the Argument I had propos'd againſt the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm,</hi> in its due light, by giving as diſtinct and clear an Account as I can, of the Nature of thoſe Parts of Poſitive Worſhip which we call Sacraments, and applying it to the Subject in diſpute.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall ſhew the inſufficiency of the Biſhop's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this Argument.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall ſet the Argument I had propos'd againſt the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm</hi> in its due light, by giving a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and clear Account of the Nature of thoſe Parts of Poſitive Worſhip which we call Sacraments, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying it to the Subject in diſpute:</p>
            <p>And this is the more neceſſary, not only becauſe the uncertain ſignification of the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd this Subject in great obſcurity and confuſion, but eſpecially becauſe the Account which the Biſhop gives of it, (when he ſuppoſes us ill-inſtructed in it, and propoſes to inform us better) ſeems to me not only
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62574:33"/> indiſtinct, but alſo very <hi>lame</hi> and <hi>defective,</hi> omitting ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral conſiderable uſes of Sacraments, which were the chief ſtrength of this Argument againſt the <hi>Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two Ordinances of Poſitive Worſhip pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd in the New Teſtament, viz. <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord's-Supper:</hi> There have been two Names invented and frequently us'd among Chriſtian Writers, to ſignifie the common nature of theſe two Inſtitutions, that of <hi>Myſteries</hi> in the Greek Church, and that of <hi>Sacraments</hi> in the Latin, a word probably borrow'd from the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary <hi>Oath</hi> which Soldiers took with certain Rites ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that end, and which was call'd the <hi>Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sacrament.</hi> But 'tis the thing it ſelf we are concern'd to enquire into. Now if we can fix upon the true ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Notion, wherein theſe two Ordinances of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord's-Supper</hi> agree, we may thence eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infer what a <hi>Divine Sacrament</hi> is: For of that I am now ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>And if we attentively conſider this Matter, we may ſoon obſerve, that thoſe two Ordinances of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> agree in this, that they are <hi>Foede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rites,</hi> or <hi>Sacred Ceremonies inſtituted by God for Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Solemnizing the Covenant between him and us.</hi> And on the other hand, in this they differ, that the former is the Sacred Rite, whereby that Covenant is firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly <hi>Enter'd</hi> into; the latter is that whereby 'tis <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd.</hi> And accordingly theſe Poſitive Inſtitutions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, ſucceed in the place of two parallel Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, or foederal Rites under the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> viz. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and the <hi>Feaſts upon Sacrifices.</hi> By the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were <hi>initiated</hi> into that Covenant made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed: By the <hi>latter</hi> their League of Amity and Peace with God, was (upon the Attonement made by Sacrifices) <hi>renew'd by theſe Feaſts</hi> upon 'em. Of which more may occur anon.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Sacred Rites that are appointed by God, both in our firſt publick <hi>Entrance</hi> into the Covenant, and our publick <hi>Renewal</hi> of it at the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Table,</hi> are deſign'd for ſeveral uſes, and principally for the three follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:62574:34"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>As repreſenting ſigns for Inſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>As obliging ſigns to Confirm and Ratifie the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Enter'd into.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>As diſtinguiſhing Signs</hi> or <hi>Badges of our Profeſſion, and the Relations we thereby are inveſted in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe uſes of 'em muſt be carefully and diſtinctly conſider'd.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Theſe Sacred Rites are us'd in theſe two Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as <hi>Repreſenting Signs for Inſtruction.</hi> (The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely wiſe God condeſcending herein to our infirmity and weakneſs.)</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>waſhing with Water,</hi> which is the Rite appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> is by its reſemblance <hi>inſtructive</hi> to us, both concerning the <hi>Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Duties</hi> of the Covenant we enter into.</p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Priviledges,</hi> Thus 'tis deſign'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent our Natural <hi>pollution</hi> and defilement, and the neceſſity of the <hi>Regenerating</hi> and <hi>Purifying</hi> Vertue of the Holy Spirit. And hence we are ſaid to be <hi>born of Water and the Holy Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 <hi>John</hi> 5.</note> i. e. formed to a new and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Life by that ſanctifying efficacy of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> which is compar'd to the purifying Vertue of <hi>Water.</hi> And elſewhere in alluſion to this Baptiſmal Rite, we are ſaid to be <hi>Saved by the Laver of Regeneration, and the Renewing of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 3 Tit. 5.</p>
            <p>Nay, this Rite ſeems alſo deſign'd to inſtruct us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our <hi>Guilt,</hi> as well as <hi>Pollution,</hi> and of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of our being <hi>Cleans'd</hi> from it by the <hi>Laver</hi> of our Mediatour's Blood. For the moſt judicious Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors underſtand thoſe words of <hi>Ananias</hi> concerning the <hi>Remiſſion of Sins,</hi> when he ſaith to <hi>Saul</hi> upon his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, <hi>Ariſe and be Baptized, and waſh away thy Sins,</hi> (or be thou waſht from thy Sins, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>calling on the Name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> 22 Acts 16. And accordingly ſuch a <hi>cleanſing</hi> virtue is aſcrib'd to the Redeemer's <hi>blood,</hi> and that Expreſſion of his <hi>Waſhing us from our Sins, in it,</hi> ſeems to carry an Alluſion to this Sacred Baptiſmal Rite. See 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:62574:34"/>
            <p>The ſame Sacred Rite is deſigned to repreſent our <hi>Duty</hi> to us, <hi>viz.</hi> To renounce the Defilements of Sin and of the World, and to conſecrate our ſelves to a Life of Holineſs, as Chriſt's purified peculiar People. And this uſe of it the Biſhop omits in his Account. To this Rite thoſe Expreſſions ſeem to refer, <hi>Such were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, ye are ſanctified,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.11. And thus the Apoſtle ſuppoſes in our Baptiſm, that there is a Reſemblance of our <hi>Dying with Christ, and our Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with him,</hi> that ſhould inſtruct us in our Duty, <hi>to Dye to Sin, and Live to Righteouſneſs,</hi> 6 Rom. 3, 4, 5. 2 Col. 12. For our <hi>Dying to Sin</hi> and <hi>Walking in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Life,</hi> is not ſignified in Baptiſm as the Benefit confer'd by God, as the Biſhop ſeems to ſuppoſe, but rather as the Duty requir'd from us, tho' the renewing and purifying efficacy of the Holy Spirit, whereby we are enabled to do ſo, is ſignify'd as a Benefit which we receive from God.</p>
            <p>The ſame I might obſerve concerning that other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> in whoſe Sacred Rites there is not only a <hi>Commemorative Repreſentation</hi> of the <hi>Death of Chriſt,</hi> but alſo an <hi>Instructive Repreſentation</hi> of our Spiritual <hi>Communion with him in his Body and Blood, (viz.</hi> in the precious Fruits of his Sacrifice,) and of thoſe Duties or Exerciſes of our Faith and Devotion to him, by which we are ſaid to <hi>Eat his Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Drink his Blood,</hi> 6 John 53, 54.</p>
            <p>I might obſerve the ſame concerning thoſe two paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Inſtitutions under the Old Teſtament, <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Religious Feasts upon Sacrifices.</hi> But this uſe of Sacraments being ſo obvious, I ſhall not inſiſt any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon it, but only add, That tho' I ſuppoſe all <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental</hi> Signs to be <hi>Repreſenting</hi> ones, and to carry ſuch an Inſtructive Reſemblance and Alluſion, yet I do not ſuppoſe all barely <hi>instructive</hi> Signs to be <hi>Sacramental</hi> or <hi>Foederal</hi> ones. For there ſeems to be more requiſite to ſuch</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Sacred Rites in <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> are intended alſo as <hi>obliging Signs to Confirm and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie that Covenant that is then Enter'd into or Renew'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:62574:35"/>
            <p>'Tis evidently ſo in <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> for the Sacred Rite there us'd is both,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>An obliging Sign on God's part;</hi> whereby he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms and ratifies the Promiſes of his Covenant to all that are intereſſed therein, even that grand comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Promiſe of being the <hi>God of the Faithful, and of their Seed,</hi> and particularly that eminent Promiſe of the <hi>Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> See 17 <hi>Gen.</hi> 7, 11. and compare it with 2 <hi>Acts</hi> 38, 39. <hi>Repent and be Baptiz'd every one of you for the Remiſſion of Sins, and ye ſhall receive the Gift of the Holy Ghost; for the Promiſe is to you and your Children,</hi> &amp;c. And our being Baptiz'd into the <hi>Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit,</hi> implys his engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be a reconcil'd Father, Redeemer and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier, to all that ſincerely devote themſelves to him.</p>
            <p>So in that other Foederal Rite of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi>
               <note place="margin">22 <hi>Luke</hi> 20.</note> 'tis ſaid of the <hi>Cup,</hi> That 'tis the <hi>New Testament in the Blood of Christ,</hi> i. e. This Sacred Memorial of his Blood is like an Authentick <hi>Seal</hi> ſet to the New Teſtament, wherein ſo many precious Legacies are convey'd to us as the Fruits of his Death and Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>And the ſame may alſo be obſerv'd concerning <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,</hi> both in the place fore-quoted 17 <hi>Gen.</hi> 7, 11— and in its being call'd by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, (viz.</hi> of that right to impunity and life, which <hi>Abraham</hi> was as a Believer entitled to thro' the Merits of that Redeemer, who was his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Seed) 4 <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>So in their Religious Feaſts upon Sacrifices, God's admitting the Offerers or Gueſts to his Table, was a ſolemn Ratification of the League of Amity and Peace renew'd between em, thro' the virtue of that future at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toning Sacrifice of Chriſt, of which the Legal ones were only Types and Figures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Sacred Rite of <hi>waſhing with Water</hi> in <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> is no leſs an <hi>obliging Sign from us to God, whereby we bind our ſelves to the Duties of his Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:62574:35"/>
            <p>Now this important uſe of a Sacrament, the Biſhop not only omits in his Deſcription of it, but plainly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that it belongs to its nature. For <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 180. he aſſerts it to me a Miſtake concerning Sacraments, to ſuppoſe. <hi>That they are Signs from us to God;</hi> whereas he affirms 'em to be <hi>wholly</hi> (for only) <hi>Signs from God to us:</hi> I confeſs this ſeems very ſurpri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, becauſe if this be a Miſtake, 'tis ſuch a Miſtake as he himſelf has run into in his <hi>Diſcourſe:</hi> For there <hi>p.</hi> 4. he gives this reaſon, <q rend="inline">Why the Celebration of the Sacraments is a part of Outward Worſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe in them we not only expreſs our dependence on God for his grace, but likewiſe oblige and bind our ſelves to ſerve him.</q> Now how this can be true, without making the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Rite a <hi>Sign from us to God,</hi> of that obligation to his Service, I cannot comprehend. So that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſeems to me in this Particular inconſiſtent with himſelf, and ſpeaks more accurately of theſe Matters, where his Partiality to his Cauſe does not miſlead his Judgment. But ſince he now aſſerts this to be a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, and demands ſome place of Scripture to prove this Notion, of a Sacraments being a <hi>Sign from us to God,</hi> (See <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 180.) I ſhall endeavour herein to give him all reaſonable ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>And this Account of Sacraments I ſhall particularly prove, in reference to <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which is the Sacrament in diſpute.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is a <hi>Sign from us to God of our Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Duties of his Covenant,</hi> as well as a <hi>Sign from God to us of the Truth of his Promiſes,</hi> is evident from the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi>'s ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Deſcription of that <hi>Internal</hi> and <hi>Saving Baptiſm</hi> which the <hi>External Waſhing</hi> is the Sign of, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.25.</note> That <hi>'tis not the putting away the filth of the Fleſh,</hi> (i. e. <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is not meerly or principally that) <hi>but the Anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God.</hi> Which words manifeſtly allude to the Covenant-Tranſaction that paſſes between the great God and the Adult Perſon baptiz'd, (for of ſuch the Apoſtle here ſpeaks) and to the <hi>Questions</hi> that were to that end propos'd to ſuch as
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62574:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:62574:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:62574:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:62574:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:62574:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:62574:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:62574:39"/> receiv'd this Seal of God's Covenant. They were ask't, <hi>If they believ'd in the Lord Jeſus with all their heart?</hi> (See 8 <hi>Acts</hi> 37.) or, as ſome ancient Chriſtian Writers propoſe the Queſtion, <q rend="inline">If they recounc'd the Devil and his Angels, the World and its Pomps? If they believ'd in, If they devoted themſelves to the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt? &amp;c.</q> And their ſincere Profeſſion and Promiſe of doing ſo, which in <hi>Baptiſm</hi> they ratified by this External Rite of Waſhing with Water, is that which the Apoſtle here calls the <hi>Anſwer of a good Conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.</hi> So that the Apoſtle was ſo far from ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was not a <hi>Sign from us to God,</hi> that he rather defines it by this part of its end and uſe, <hi>viz.</hi> To be a Solemn Rite whereby we profeſs to engage our Hearts to the Duties of his Covenant. And indeed ſince <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is the Solemnizing a mutual Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Bleſſed God on the one part, and our Selves or our Seed on the other, it is firſt a <hi>Sign from us to God,</hi> of our Conſent to the propoſed Terms of his Covenant, before it can be a <hi>Sign from him to us,</hi> of our or our Childrens intereſt in thoſe Benefits of his Covenant that preſuppoſe our conſent as the Condition thereof. 'Tis the <hi>Baptiſm of Repentance for the Remiſſion of Sins,</hi> 1 Mark 4. and is therefore firſt a <hi>Sign</hi> of our <hi>Repentance</hi> towards God, before it can be a <hi>Sign</hi> from him of the <hi>Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> And ſo 'tis propos'd by the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> at the firſt time we read of its Adminiſtration to his Adult Converts, 2 <hi>Acts</hi> 38, 39. <hi>Repent and be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized every one of you in the Name of Chriſt for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins, for the Promiſe is unto you and your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> Where they were by Baptiſm firſt to profeſs their Repentance towards God, and Faith in our Lord Jeſus, and then receive the promiſed Benefit, <hi>Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> Nay, Chriſt's own Command to his Apoſtles, firſt, to <hi>Diſciple</hi> or <hi>Proſelyte all Nations,</hi> and then to <hi>Baptize 'em,</hi> plainly implys that one great uſe of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was to be a ſolemn Bond upon 'em, to the Duties of that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Profeſſion they had embrac'd, and the <hi>Baptizing 'em in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit,</hi> has been always ſuppos'd to imply a Solemn <hi>Dedication</hi> of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62574:39"/>
'em by this Sacred Rite to the Faith, Worſhip, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of that Bleſſed Trinity, into whoſe Name they are Baptized. There is in that Inſtitution a <hi>Seal</hi> ſet to the Covenant of God on our part, as well as on his: To which 'tis not improbable that thoſe words of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> refer, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. —<hi>Nevertheleſs the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> (or as ſome reader the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Tabula con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractus,</hi> the Covenant) <hi>of God stands ſure, having this Seal</hi> (on God's part) <hi>The Lord knows them that are his;</hi> and (this Seal on our part) <hi>Let him that names the Name of Christ depart from iniquity.</hi> As the Covenant is mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, ſo the External Rite is intended to ratifie our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtipulation</hi> as well as God's <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and accordingly our breach of the Baptiſmal Covenant by Apoſtaſie or Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity is Perjury, and therefore ſo often in the Scripture Language repreſented by the breach of the Conjugal Vow, that the Adultereſs is guilty of. And this Notion of Baptiſm as an <hi>obliging Sign from God to us,</hi> is the more unreaſonably deny'd by the Biſhop, if we conſider, that 'tis this very uſe of Baptiſm, that chiefly occaſion'd the Name of a Sacrament being given to it, becauſe Baptiſm was reckon'd (like the Military Oath of the Roman Soldiers) as a ſolemn Liſting the Perſon Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd into the Service and Warfare of Chriſt againſt the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil. So that the Biſhop has excluded that from the nature and notion of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which was the chief, if not the only ground, of this Rite of the Chriſtian Religion being called one.</p>
            <p>And it were as eaſie to ſhew the ſame concerning the other Inſtitutions that are call'd <hi>Sacraments.</hi> Thus as <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was a Token of the Covenant between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed in their Generations; ſo 'twas an <hi>obliging Sign</hi> on their part, as well as on God's part. It oblig'd them to receive and obey the Revelations of the Divine Will to 'em. And hence, after the delivery of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Circumciſion was an External Bond on thoſe that receiv'd it to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that <hi>Law;</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> plainly intimates to us, 5 <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. —He that was <hi>Circumcis'd made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62574:40"/> a Debtor to the Law to do it;</hi> i. e. brought himſelf under a ſolemn Tye thereto by this External Rite.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Feaſts upon Sacrifices</hi> under the Law were Foederal Rites (in alluſion to the general Cuſtom of thoſe Eaſtern Nations, to Confirm mutual Covenants by <hi>Eating and Drinking together;</hi> See 26 <hi>Gen.</hi> 30, 31.31 <hi>Gen.</hi> 44, 45, 46. 9 <hi>Joſ.</hi> 14.41 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.5 <hi>Lam.</hi> 6. <hi>Obad.</hi> 7. v.) is ſo largely prov'd by the Learned Dr. <hi>Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> in his excellent Treatiſe on the <hi>Lord's Supper and Feaſt upon a Sacrifice,</hi> that I ſhall refer the Reader to it for fuller ſatisfaction. And that one paſſage in the 50 <hi>Pſalm</hi> v. 5. is ſufficient to put it out of doubt; <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my Saints together, thoſe that have made a Covenant with me by Sacrifice.</hi> Now the Covenant was made and celebrated, not meerly by <hi>Offering</hi> it up, but chiefly by their Religious Feaſt upon it.</p>
            <p>And as the Lord's Supper ſucceeds in the place and ſtead of thoſe Jewiſh Feaſts upon Sacrifices, ſo 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently deſign'd as ſuch a Foederal Rite, whereby we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new our League of Peace with God, upon the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials of the Attoning Sacrifice of his own Son by our renewed Conſent to the Terms of his Covenant: And hence the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> warns his <hi>Corinthian</hi> Converts againſt the Idolatrous Practice of Feaſting in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Heathen Idols, as inconſiſtent with the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations which their Feaſting at the Lord's Table had laid upon 'em to be the Worſhippers of the only true God, who was too jealous of his own Honor to admit of any Rival in it. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 <hi>ch.</hi> from the fourteenth to the twenty third verſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Theſe Foederal Rites of Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper muſt be conſider'd as intended alſo to be <hi>diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Signs of our Chriſtian Profeſſion, and the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which we are thereby inveſted in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus our Baptiſm is the honourable Badge of our Diſcipleſhip, whereby we are diſcriminated from the Infidel World. We do hereby put on the Livery of Chriſt, (as thoſe words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> imply,— 3 <hi>Gal.</hi> 27. <hi>For a many of you as have been Baptized into Christ, have put on Christ.</hi>) And therefore he adds, they
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62574:40"/> were no more to be diſtinguiſh'd into <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Greek,</hi> &amp;c. but <hi>all were one in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> This one <hi>Livery</hi> was to be the common Sign of their belonging to him as their one Lord and Maſter. And accordingly, our partaking of one External Baptiſm, is made a Mark and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of thoſe that belong'd to that one viſible <hi>Body,</hi> or Church of which Chriſt is the <hi>Lord</hi> and Head, as our partaking of one Internal Baptiſm is the certain Mark of our belonging to the one inviſible Church, or myſtical Body of Chriſt. See 1 <hi>Eph.</hi> 4, 5, 6. To the ſame purpoſe we read elſewhere, that <hi>we are by one Spirit baptized into one Body, whether we be Jews or Gentiles, whether we be bond or free,</hi> and have been all made to drink into one Spirit. The latter words, of being <hi>made to drink into one Spirit,</hi> according to the general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the beſt Expoſiters, refer to the Lord's Supper, as the former do to Baptiſm. And the words plainly imply, that Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper are the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol and the Bond of our External Communion, as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the viſible Church, as by partaking of the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying Operations of the ſame Holy Spirit, we become Members of one myſtical Body of Chriſt. So that by our Baptiſm we are incorporated into the Chriſtian Community, and thereby diſcriminated in our right to its External Priviledges from them that are without, who are yet <hi>Aliens</hi> and <hi>Foreigners.</hi> And ſo by the Lord's Supper we are, as <hi>partakers of Christ's Holy Table,</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd from them that <hi>partake of the Table of Devils,</hi> and <hi>are in fellowſhip</hi> (or Communion) <hi>with them</hi>— 1 Cor. 10.20, 21.</p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>Circumciſion</hi> the diſcriminating Mark of theſe that embrac'd the <hi>Faith of Abraham,</hi> from ſuch as were <hi>Aliens from the Commonwealth of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and Strangers to the Covenants of Promiſe. Circumciſed and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed</hi> was equivalent to one that did, or did not own the Jewiſh Religion.</p>
            <p>Having thus far clear'd the general <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> of theſe two Inſtitutions in the Chriſtian Religion which we call <hi>Sacraments,</hi> (for all the particular uſes of each of 'em, I am not now concern'd to conſider) I come to apply this Account to the Matter in Debate.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:62574:41"/>
            <p>And accordingly, 'tis obvious to any that ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the foregoing Account, that there is one <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of theſe Foederal or <hi>Sacramental Rites</hi> that does neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſuppoſe Divine Inſtitution, viz. <hi>Their being obliging ſigns on God's part to ratifie his Promiſes.</hi> For it were too abſurd for any to imagine that God will oblige himſelf by ſigns he never appointed for that end. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Papiſts themſelves pretend their new Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be <hi>Divine</hi> ones, by feigning God's Inſtitution for 'em.</p>
            <p>When therefore I ſpeak of a <hi>Human Sacrament,</hi> I mean no more by it, <q rend="inline">than an External Rite ſet up by meer Human Authority, without any pretence of Divine Inſtitution, for ſeveral Sacramental Uſes, ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtitute it as truly a part of Religious Worſhip as Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper are.</q> So that it wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but God's Inſtituting it to be a <hi>Seal</hi> to <hi>his</hi> part of the Covenant, as Men have made it a <hi>Seal</hi> to <hi>their</hi> part, to render it as proper a <hi>Sacrament</hi> as either of the two former. And 'tis only in this ſenſe that I ſuppoſe the <hi>Croſs</hi> to be made a <hi>Human Sacrament</hi> by the eſtabliſht Church. 'Tis made by 'em a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> as far as Men can make <hi>one</hi> of a Religious Rite that they can pretend no Divine Authority for. And this is ſufficient to prove it a ſinful Human Invention, as I ſhall now ſhow, in proſecuting the Particulars here ſuggeſted.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <q rend="inline">The Croſs is ſet up for ſeveral Sacramental Uſes, <hi>even the like <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes as</hi> Baptiſm <hi>and the</hi> Lord's Supper <hi>are appointed for.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For according to the foregoing Account of theſe Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deral or Sacramental Rites,</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis <hi>ſet up as a Repreſenting or Inſtructive ſign.</hi> And that both in the Duties and the Benefits of the New Covenant.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſet up as <hi>Inſtructive</hi> in the Duties of it. And this the Biſhop grants when he owns, (<hi>Admon.</hi> p. 178.) <q rend="inline">That the Croſs is us'd to ſignifie the Return we ought to make to God, for the Benefits receiv'd in Baptiſm.</q> And indeed the words of the <hi>Service-Book</hi> put this out of doubt: <hi>We ſign this Child,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in token that he ſhall
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62574:41"/> not be aſhamed to Confeſs the Faith of Chriſt crucified,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſet up as <hi>Instructive</hi> in the <hi>Benefits</hi> of the New Covenant. This indeed the Biſhop denys in the place laſt quoted; and tells us, <hi>The Croſs is not us'd by 'em to ſignifie any Grace or Benefit communicated from God.</hi> But I think there is juſt ground to conclude the contrary from the Reaſon which the Convocation alledges for Retaining the uſe of the <hi>Sign of the Croſs,</hi> viz. <q rend="inline">That the Holy Ghoſt by the Mouth of the Apoſtles did ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the name of the Croſs ſo far, that under it he comprehended not only Chriſt crucified, but the force, effect and merit of his Death and Paſſion, with all the comforts, fruits and promiſes we receive or expect thereby.</q> See the Thirtieth Canon of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Now I would gladly know what this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can ſignifie to vindicate their retaining the uſe of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> unleſs they ſuppoſed it a fit external <hi>Sign</hi> to ſignifie the ſame things which the Holy Ghoſt had ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd the <hi>Name</hi> of the <hi>Croſs</hi> to ſignifie. And this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference ſeems the more juſt, from the account they give of this Ceremony of <hi>Croſſing,</hi> as practis'd by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">That they ſigned their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with the Sign of the Croſs when they were Chriſten'd, to dedicate 'em by that Badge to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, whoſe Benefits beſtow'd on 'em in Baptiſm, the name of the Croſs did repreſent.</q> And conſequently, the <hi>Sign</hi> of it is deſign'd to repreſent too.</p>
            <p>But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Which is more conſiderable, The <hi>Croſs</hi> is made by the eſtabliſht Church <hi>an obliging and ratifying ſign on our part,</hi> to bind us to the Duties of God's Covenant, even to the ſame which Baptiſm is appointed to oblige us to, viz. <q rend="inline">To confeſs boldly the Faith of Christ crucified, To fight manfully under his Banner againſt the Fleſh, the World, and the Devil, and to continue Christ's faithful Soldiers and Servants to our lives end.</q> And I may ſtill renew the <hi>Queſtion</hi> propos'd in the <hi>Remarks, What more peculiar Duties of the New Covenant could Baptiſm ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us to?</hi> And to put the matter, if poſſible, out of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62574:42"/> doubt, the Infant is expreſly ſaid in the <hi>Canon</hi> to be by this <hi>Badge dedicated to the Service of Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Coll. of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, 2d Edit p. 377, 378.</note> I know indeed the ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Author of the Caſe relating to the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm,</hi> diſtinguiſhes here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween and <hi>immediate</hi> and <hi>proper,</hi> and an <hi>improper</hi> and <hi>declarative Dedication,</hi> and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would perſwade us that the <hi>Convocation</hi> only deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the latter; partly, becauſe they refer to the words us'd in the <hi>Service Book</hi> when the Child is <hi>croſs't,</hi> partly becauſe they ſuppoſe the Child dedicated by <hi>Baptiſm</hi> before, and ſuppoſe <hi>Baptiſm</hi> compleat without the ſign of the <hi>Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſee not that either of theſe Reaſons warrant us to take the words of the <hi>Convocation</hi> in ſo very ſtrain'd and improper a ſenſe as this is, <hi>viz.</hi> That when they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the <hi>Croſs to be a lawful outward Ceremony, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Badge whereby the Infant is dedicated to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of him that died on the Croſs,</hi> they ſhould mean no more than that 'tis a lawful outward Ceremony and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Badge, to declare that the Infant has been dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to Chriſt by another outward Ceremony and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Badge before. For 'tis evident that the <hi>words</hi> us'd when the Child is <hi>ſign'd</hi> with the <hi>ſign</hi> of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> do as fully and directly expreſs a proper immediate Dedication, as the <hi>words</hi> us'd when 'tis Baptiz'd, and therefore we have no reaſon from them to apply ſo unuſual and odd a ſenſe to the words of the <hi>Canon,</hi> and the <hi>Convocations</hi> ſuppoſing <hi>Baptiſm</hi> compleat without the <hi>ſign</hi> of the <hi>Croſs;</hi> does no way Argue that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd not a proper renew'd Dedication by the <hi>Croſs;</hi> for tho' we are dedicated by <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> yet we properly renew that Dedication as oft as we attend the <hi>Lord's Table.</hi> And the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> does in, their <hi>Ritual,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Rit. Rom. Paris <hi>1635.</hi> p. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> ſuppoſe no more neceſſary by Divine Right to this Sacrament than we do, and ſpeak of their Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies as only pertaining to the Solemnity of that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, yet they uſe ſeveral other Rites for proper im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Dedication, beſides that of waſhing with water</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:62574:42"/>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Croſs</hi> is made a <hi>diſtinguiſhing ſign of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſſion, and the Relations we are thereby invested in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this evidently follows from its being made the <hi>Honourable Badge of our Dedication to the Service of a crucified Saviour.</hi> So that by being <hi>croſs't,</hi> we do truly (according to the eſtabliſht Church) wear the <hi>Livery</hi> of Chriſt, as by being <hi>Baptiz'd.</hi> And this <hi>former</hi> Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſign is as effectually made the common Symbol and Teſſera of our Diſcipleſhip, the mark of our belonging to him as our Lord and Maſter, as the <hi>latter</hi> can be.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Now from hence I farther infer, That the <hi>Croſs</hi> is made as much a Sacrament as Men can make any ſign of their own, for which they can produce no Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution. 'Tis ſet up for moſt of the ſame uſes as <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> nay for ſuch uſes as do conſtitute it a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per part of poſitive Worſhip, that has no ſtamp of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority, and conſequently 'tis made a ſinful Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Invention. For if (as the Biſhop himſelf ſuppoſes) <hi>all ways of Worſhip are diſpleaſing to God, that are not expreſly contained in the Holy Scriptures, nor warranted by the Examples of Holy Man therein,</hi> or (as he now adds) <hi>that cannot be by parity of Reaſon deduc'd thence;</hi> much more are all parts of Worſhip truly diſpleaſing to him, (and ſuch as our Saviour juſtly cenſures for <hi>vain Worſhip</hi>) that are no way Inſtituted. And yet, that all thoſe Rites in Religious Worſhip, whereby we <hi>oblige and bind our ſelves to ſerve God,</hi> or (which is the ſame) <hi>Dedicate our ſelves to his Service,</hi> are a proper part of Poſitive Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is evident from the Biſhop's own confeſſion, who (<hi>p.</hi> 4. of his <hi>Diſcourſe</hi>) does therefore make the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be a part of outward Worſhip, not only on the account of our expreſſing therein, our dependance on the grace of God, but likewiſe on the account of obliging and binding our ſelves by 'em to ſerve him.</hi> And doubtleſs, it does as properly belong to God alone to appoint the Religious Rites whereby we bind our ſelves to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as to the Supreme Magiſtrate to appoint the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies us'd in our taking the <hi>Oath of Fidelity and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</hi> Nay it belongs to him alone to appoint the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62574:43"/> Badge of our Diſcipleſhip,</hi> who receives us into his Holy Covenant; and no inferiour Paſtors are any more authoriz'd to ſuperadd any other Rite for this uſe, to that he has Inſtituted already, than the Servant of any great Prince is warranted of his own Head to preſcribe to his Fellow-ſervants the wearing of a new <hi>Livery,</hi> as an <hi>Honourable Badge</hi> of their belonging to ſuch a Maſter, beſides that which he has appointed of his own chooſing. To ſet up External Rites for ſuch Sacramental uſes as theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> not only to inſtruct us in the Priviledges and Duties of the New Covenant, but <hi>to oblige and bind us to 'em,</hi> and to be the <hi>Honourable Badge of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Profeſſion,</hi> when God has already inſtituted other Rites for theſe very ends, is a piece of Preſumption we dare not be guilty of: 'Tis an offering him a part of Worſhip which has no ſtamp of his Authority, which therefore we have no reaſon to hope he will accept; nay, which there is no ſhadow of Reaſon for, if his own Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deral Rites be ſufficient for all the ends they are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſtared my <hi>Argument,</hi> I come</p>
            <p n="2">II. To ſhew the inſufficiency of the Biſhop's Anſwer to this Argument.</p>
            <p>All that I can find, he has directly reply'd to my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, is only this; <q rend="inline">That the whole force of it ſeems to proceed from two Miſtakes concerning the nature of Sacraments: Firſt, As if they were ſigns from us to God, and not wholly from God to us. Secondly, As if we were to learn the true Nature of Sacraments from the Schools and partial Definitions of intereſſed Diſputants, and not from the Holy Scriptures Hence, <hi>ſaith the Biſhop,</hi> he has not given us one place of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to prove his imperfect Account of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As to this Anſwer to the Argument, I need do no more for the Refutation of it, than refer the Reader to the foregoing Account of a Sacrament, wherein I fully prov'd concerning Sacraments in general, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly that of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> that they are as truly and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſigns from us to God,</hi> as <hi>from God to us;</hi> nay, that they
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62574:43"/> cannot be the latter without being the former. And this I have prov'd, not from the Dictates of the Schools, but from the <hi>Oracles of God;</hi> having quoted no other <hi>Human Authority</hi> but his <hi>own,</hi> and I hope he will not reckon himſelf one of thoſe Partial and Intereſſed Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putants he ſpeaks of. So that 'tis not the force of my Argument, but of his Anſwer, that proceeds from a <hi>Miſtake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſuppoſe his Lordſhip may lay more ſtreſs upon his Account of a Sacrament, and his Application of it to vindicate the <hi>Croſs,</hi> which therefore I ſhall alſo briefly conſider.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe he acquaints us, <q rend="inline">There are Three things neceſſary to make up a Sacrament.</q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Firſt, An outward viſible ſign inſtituted by God, ſignifying ſome Spiritual Grace we expect from him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, An Obligation on God by ſome Promiſe of his to grant us that Spiritual Grace or Benefit whenever we duly uſe the viſible Sign.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Our uſe of this viſible Sign, without which we are not to expect the Spiritual Benefit if we wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully neglect it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Accordingly the Biſhop thinks me obliged to prove that Theſe things concur in the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm,</hi> viz That the eſtabliſht Church teaches that the <hi>Croſs</hi> is inſtituted by God to ſignifie ſome Spiritual Grace we expect from him, and that he has oblig'd himſelf by Promiſe to grant us that Spiritual Grace upon the uſe of the Croſs, and will deprive us thereof if we neglect it.</p>
            <p>Now to ſhew the inſufficiency and weakneſs of this <hi>Anſwer,</hi> I need only ſuggeſt theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Biſhop has in this Account of <hi>Sacraments</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſeveral of thoſe uſes and ends for which they were appointed, and particularly thoſe from whence the force of this Argument is deriv'd. For he neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders their being made <hi>repreſenting</hi> ſigns to inſtruct us in the <hi>duties</hi> of the New Covenant, nor (which ſhould have been chiefly obſerv'd) their being <hi>obliging</hi> ſigns to bind us to 'em, nor their being <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> badges of our Profeſſion and Communion. And yet theſe are very
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62574:44"/> important uſes of thoſe Foederal Rites of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and ſuch as chiefly occaſioned their being call'd <hi>Sacraments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He expects I ſhould prove that which my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment no way obliges me to, <hi>viz.</hi> That the eſtabliſht Church teaches, that God has oblig'd himſelf by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to grant us ſome Spiritual Benefit upon our uſe of the ſign of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and will deny that Benefit to all that neglect that ſign. Now tho' he might juſtly have expected me to prove this, if I had ſaid, That the eſtabliſht Church feigns the <hi>Croſs</hi> to be a <hi>Sacrament of God's appointment,</hi> and uſes it as ſuch; yet 'tis evident from the foregoing Account, that 'tis unreaſonable to expect it in what I call a <hi>Human Sacrament.</hi> For when I ſuppoſe it made a <hi>Human Sacrament,</hi> I intend no more, then that 'tis made a <hi>Sacrament</hi> as far as Men can make one of a Religious Rite of their own. Now they may make it a ſacred Foederal Rite to <hi>oblige and bind themſelves to God's ſervice;</hi> tho' 'tis abſurd to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect they ſhould make it a Rite to <hi>oblige God to confer his Benefits.</hi> And their ſetting it up to this <hi>former</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental uſe (as well as other uſes aforementioned) is ſufficient, as I have ſhewn him from his own Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to make it a ſinful <hi>Human Invention,</hi> as every <hi>part</hi> of Worſhip is that has no ſtamp of Divine Authority. So that I can eaſily allow the Biſhop, without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to my Argument, That to be a Seal of God's part of the Covenant, is ſo neceſſary to a true and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Sacrament, that what wants that, is but the life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Image of one. But Men may preſumptuouſly appoint Rites of their own to ſo many <hi>Sacramental uſes</hi> as ſhall as truly render 'em Parts of Divine Worſhip as Divine Sacraments are, tho' they do not ſuppoſe God oblig'd to confer his Benefits on all that uſe them. And by doing ſo, they ſet up ſuch <hi>vain Worſhip</hi> as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour condemns, as only taught by the Precepts of Men, 15 <hi>Matth.</hi> 8, 9. compar'd with 29 <hi>Iſai.</hi> 13. So that the Biſhop here only cavils at the name of <hi>Human Sacraments,</hi> while he overlooks the plain force and ſtreſs of the Argument, which depends not on the <hi>Name</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:62574:44"/> at all, but on the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes,</hi> for which the <hi>Croſs</hi> is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And I have ſhew'd 'tis appointed for all but that <hi>one</hi> that neceſſarily ſuppoſes <hi>Divine Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the Biſhop now pretends to a <hi>Divine Warrant</hi> for the uſe of the <hi>Croſs</hi> to thoſe purpoſes for which he ſuppoſes it appointed by the eſtabliſht Church, 'tis requiſite I ſhould conſider what he has offer'd on that Head.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Biſhop undertakes to ſhew, <hi>That the uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm is warranted by Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Argument to prove this is drawn out to a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable length, from <hi>p.</hi> 181. to <hi>p.</hi> 187. And that I may not wrong him in contracting it, I ſhall take this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in what I ſhall offer againſt it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſhew, That the Biſhop's Argument does not reach the main uſe of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> which he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to defend.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall ſhew that the fame Argument will juſtifie many other Rites added by the <hi>Romiſh Church to Baptiſm,</hi> and other parts of Worſhip, which they have rejected as well as we.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall conſider the diſtinct Propoſitions the Biſhop has laid down, and ſhew where I judge the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument in 'em to be weak and unconcluding.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſhew that the Biſhop's Argument does not reach the main uſe the <hi>Croſs</hi> which he was concern'd to defend.</p>
            <p>For he was chiefly oblig'd to defend the Croſs's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a <hi>Dedicating ſign,</hi> whereby we <hi>bind our ſelves to the ſervice of Christ,</hi> and thereby a common <hi>diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Badge</hi> of our Chriſtian Profeſſion; whereas in his Argument he attempts to prove no more, than that the Scripture does warrant our uſing it as an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive ſign</hi> to ſignifie or expreſs this particular Duty of our <hi>Glorying in the ſufferings of Chriſt.</hi> Now tho' I do not think he has produc'd us any clear Scriptural warrant for this very <hi>uſe</hi> of the <hi>ſign</hi> of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> yet if he had, what he has ſaid falls very far ſhort of juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe two other more important <hi>uſes</hi> of it, which are more peculiar to <hi>Foederal</hi> or <hi>Sacramental</hi> Rites, <hi>viz.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62574:45"/> It's being a Rite of Dedication</hi> to the Service of Chriſt, and thereby the <hi>Livery</hi> or <hi>Badge</hi> of the Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall ſhew that the Biſhop's Argument will ſerve as well to juſtifie many other Rites which the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> has added to <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and other parts of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> a Papiſt may from the Biſhop's Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument draw the following Plea for ſeveral other Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies added to it by the <hi>Roman Ritual;</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Prieſts putting ſalt into the mouth of the Infant, his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing his ears and noſtrils with ſpittle, his putting a lighted Taper into the Infants or Godfathers hand, his put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a white Garment on him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">We are oblig'd <hi>(ſaith the Biſhop)</hi> to expreſs the inward ſenſe of our Minds concerning God by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward means, the Scriptures command to expreſs it by our <hi>Actions</hi> as well as <hi>Words;</hi> as to theſe outward <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> we are to uſe ſuch as the general Cuſtom of our Country has made ſignificant in the like Caſes. Thus becauſe making the ſign of the Croſs is an <hi>Action,</hi> which univerſal Cuſtom has applied to ſignifie our glorying in the ſufferings of Chriſt, and 'tis proper to make a Profeſſion of doing ſo in our <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> Therefore the Scriptures warrant our uſe of it in general, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly at that time.</q> 
               <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 181, 182, 183.</p>
            <p>Since then (may the Papiſts in <hi>Italy</hi> or <hi>Spain</hi> argue) 'tis our Duty to <hi>ſavour the things of God;</hi> To have <hi>our Lips ſeaſon'd with Wiſdom and Grace; To open our Ears to the Doctrine of Christ as becomes his Diſciples; To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our Garments clean by immaculate Purity of Life, that we may appear faultleſs before the Tribunal of Chriſt; To walk in the Light by a blameleſs obſervance of our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Vows, that we may with the wiſe Virgins be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Heavenly Nuptials;</hi> Nay, ſince 'tis as proper to make a Profeſſion of all this in our <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> as of <hi>Glorying in the ſufferings of Christ:</hi> And ſince the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures warrant us to make that Profeſſion not only by <hi>Words,</hi> but alſo by ſuch <hi>Actions as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal cuſtom of our Country has made ſignificant to thoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes,</hi> we are
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62574:45"/> thereby warranted to uſe all the <hi>Rites</hi> forementioned in the Celebration of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> ſince by the <hi>univerſal cuſtom of our Country,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Rit. Rom.</note> they are applied to ſignifie our obligation to theſe undoubted Duties of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Nay, the Biſhop's Argument will go farther: For ſince 'tis as lawful to profeſs our <hi>Glorying in the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Christ</hi> in other parts of Religious Worſhip as in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and univerſal cuſtom has applied this Action to ſignifie our doing ſo, why do we not imitate, inſtead of blaming the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for their ſo frequently <hi>croſſing</hi> themſelves in all their Devotions? Or rather, ſince the Scriptures <hi>command</hi> us to expreſs the inward religious ſenſe of our Minds by <hi>Actions;</hi> nay, ſince (as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop aſſerts) Scripture-Preſidents, not only <hi>warrant</hi> but <hi>oblige</hi> us to uſe ſuch <hi>actions</hi> as well as <hi>words,</hi> as by univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal cuſtom ſignifie <hi>our glorying in the ſufferings of Chriſt.</hi> How come we to lay aſide ſo pious a cuſtom, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, nay ſo neceſſary an Expreſſion of our devout reſpect to a crucified Saviour, which we are not only <hi>warranted</hi> but <hi>oblig'd</hi> to uſe?</p>
            <p>Nay, as the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church has in other parts of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip introduc'd a great number of <hi>Actions</hi> or <hi>Rites</hi> to expreſs ſome part or other of our Chriſtian <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> or <hi>Devotion,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Actions</hi> are rendred <hi>ſignificant</hi> to that purpoſe by <hi>univerſal cuſtom</hi> among thoſe of that Church, 'tis plain by this Argument, that all thoſe <hi>Rites</hi> are warranted by <hi>Scripture,</hi> and our firſt Reformers ſeem to have been very unreaſonable in their Rejection of 'em. So that this looſe way of Reaſoning will ſerve to worſe purpoſes than I hope his Lordſhip ever deſign'd it: For it will altogether as well fit the mouth of a Papiſt, for juſtifying his obſervance of moſt of thoſe numerous Rites and Ceremonies (or in his Lordſhip's language, <hi>ſignificant Actions</hi>) which their Church has enjoyn'd, as it does his for juſtifying the <hi>Croſs in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</hi> If the Biſhop ſhould pretend that the numerouſneſs of thoſe <hi>Rites</hi> is the only fault of 'em, he would do well to acquaint us where we may ſtop, what number of 'em is innocent, and what becomes ſinfully exceſſive.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:62574:46"/>
            <p>Thirdly, I come to examine the Propoſitions the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop has laid down for proving the uſe of the <hi>Croſs</hi> in <hi>Baptiſm</hi> to be warranted by Scripture, and ſhew where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I think his Argument in 'em weak and unconclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>That we are, according to <hi>Propoſition</hi> the firſt, to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs our inward Reverence or Worſhip of God by outward Means, ſuch as Praiſe, Prayer, &amp;c.</hi> will be freely grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>That we are, according to <hi>Propoſition</hi> the ſecond and third, to expreſs that <hi>inward Worſhip</hi> in general, by ſuch <hi>bodily Gestures, as either nature or civil cuſtom di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us to,</hi> and render moſt fit to repreſent and teſtifie it to others by, will be alſo own'd. But I cannot ſo eaſily grant, That the Scriptures warrant our expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſenſe of our Minds in <hi>all Religious Things or Matters</hi> by <hi>ſignificant Actions.</hi> The particular Duties we owe to God are almoſt numberleſs; and if we were warranted by Scripture to expreſs the Thoughts and Senſe of our Mind, as to each of 'em, by ſome ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant <hi>Rite</hi> and <hi>Ceremony,</hi> the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church would be ſufficiently authoriz'd by Scripture in her introducing ſuch a load of ſignificant <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies</hi> into Chriſtian Religion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 181.</note> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if (as the Biſhop obſerves) <hi>ſuch ſignificant Actions be more effectual, and ſincere expreſſions of the ſenſe of our Minds then words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' then the Scriptures enjoyn Bodily Worſhip in general, and conſequently warrant all ſuch devout <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures</hi> as either <hi>nature</hi> or <hi>civil cuſtom</hi> has taught us to expreſs it by, as <hi>bowing, prostration, kneeling, standing,</hi> and (in theſe parts of the world) the <hi>mens being unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd,</hi> yet they do not warrant us to contrive diſtinct ſignificant Actions to expreſs each diſtinct part of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Worſhip, as <hi>one</hi> to expreſs our Faith in God, <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> to expreſs our Love to him, another our <hi>Hope,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our <hi>ſubjection to his Authority,</hi> another our <hi>reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his diſpoſal,</hi> another our <hi>dread of his Juſtice,</hi> &amp;c. So tho' we may teſtifie our Worſhip of Chriſt as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate Word, by the forementioned Poſtures of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62574:46"/> yet the Scriptures no where warrant our contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>one</hi> ſignificant Action or Rite to expreſs but <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving his Goſpel, another</hi> to expreſs our <hi>Reliance on the virtue of his Merits and Sacrifice,</hi> another to ſignifie out <hi>ſubjection to his Royal Authority,</hi> another to declare out <hi>glorying in his Croſs or Sufferings.</hi> Beſides the Religious Poſtures that are expreſſive of Worſhip in general, the Scriptures require no other External Rites as Signs of our particular reſpect to him, beſides thoſe of being <hi>Baptiz'd in his Name,</hi> and <hi>commemorating his Death by receiving the Bread and Wine as the ſacred Memorials of it.</hi> Therefore,</p>
            <p>As to the fourth and fifth <hi>Propoſition,</hi> Tho' 'tis our duty to <hi>glory in the ſufferings of Chriſt,</hi> yet the Scripture does not <hi>warrant</hi> (much leſs <hi>oblige</hi> us, as the Biſhop adds) to contrive any particular <hi>Rite</hi> or <hi>Ceremony</hi> to ſignifie it, any more than to contrive ſuch a Rite do ſignifie but <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of his Goſpel,</hi> or <hi>dependance on his Mediation,</hi> or <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to his Government.</hi> The Scriptures command our expreſſing our inward Worſhip by Reverence in our <hi>Bodily Poſtures,</hi> and conſequently <hi>uncovering the Head</hi> is to us a Particular included in that <hi>general</hi> Precept. But the Scripture no where commands us to ſignifie this particular Duty of <hi>glorying in the ſufferings of Chriſt</hi> by any External Rites, and therefore does not warrant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular Rite for that end; for that would have been to have left a Gap open for bringing in an endleſs Train of ſuch ſignificant Rites of our own deviſing, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtian Religion, even ſuch as would have made the Yoke of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> as heavy as that of <hi>Judaiſm</hi> once was.</p>
            <p>As to the ſixth and ſeventh <hi>Propoſition,</hi> it plainly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows from what has been ſuggeſted, That if the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture neither <hi>oblige</hi> nor <hi>warrant</hi> us to contrive an Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Rite for ſignifying our <hi>glorying in the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> much leſs does it warrant our uſe of it in <hi>Baptiſm</hi> where there is an External Rite appointed by Chriſt himſelf, ſufficiently expreſſive of the whole of our Duty to him. What if the ſame Authority that ſet up this very ſign of the Croſs, had appointed <hi>leaning on a material Croſs,</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:62574:47"/> to ſignifie our Faith and Reliance on the Merits of a <hi>crucified</hi> Saviour, and <hi>kiſſing a Scepter</hi> to ſignifie our <hi>Homage</hi> to him as a <hi>King,</hi> &amp;c. and had introduc'd theſe Rites into the Office of <hi>Baptiſm?</hi> Could they juſtly pretend the Scripture warranted them, becauſe it enjoyns Faith in a <hi>crucified Saviour,</hi> and <hi>ſubjection</hi> to him as our exalted <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Lord?</hi> And yet theſe would be as fit <hi>Actions</hi> to ſignifie theſe Duties, as the making that a cry ſign to expreſs our <hi>glorying in the ſufferings of Chriſt.</hi> But the Scriptures have given no countenance to ſuch fooliſh Inventions of our own, nor open'd any ſuch door to our Fancies, which if indulg'd this way, will ſoon prove very fruitful in ſuch Superſtitious Devices; as the Church has learnt by the ſad experience of ſo many A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, in which the multiplicity of ſuch Rites (or in the Biſhop's language <hi>ſignificant Actions</hi>) had almoſt eaten out the Vitals of Religion.</p>
            <p>For the eighth <hi>Propoſition,</hi> I ſhall conſider the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Inſtances of ſuch <hi>ſignificant Rites in religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> for which the Biſhop produces Scriptural-Preſidents, and by which he thinks this Ceremony of Croſſing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually warranted.</p>
            <p>For that of <hi>Chriſt's waſhing his Diſciples feet.</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee what it ſhould ſignifie to his purpoſe: For who doubts but Chriſt might teach his Diſciples <hi>Humility,</hi> by practiſing before their eyes a <hi>common,</hi> but in <hi>him</hi> a moſt condeſcending Inſtance of it; or, that he might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that occaſion, (as he did almoſt all occurrents) to remind 'em of the Neceſſity of being <hi>waſh'd in his Blood,</hi> or <hi>purify'd by his Grace.</hi> But what's this to our appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a new External Badge of our Dedication to Chriſt, beſides that he has appointed already?</p>
            <p>For the ſecond Rite of <hi>Dipping entirely under Water in Baptiſm,</hi> if the Bp. had prov'd both that the words of the Apoſtle did certainly refer to the Practice of <hi>Dipping under Water,</hi> aſſigning this <hi>Spiritual ſignification</hi> to that particular Rite, and yet that the Chriſtians of that Age had arbitrarily, and without any warrant from Chriſt or his Apoſtles, ſet up this Mode of <hi>Baptiſing</hi> as a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Rite, to ſignifie their <hi>obligation to die to ſin, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62574:47"/> live to righteouſneſs,</hi> in conformity to the Death and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt, then indeed this Inſtance had ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified ſomething to his purpoſe; but unleſs he prove both theſe Particulars, it ſignifies nothing.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Anſwer may be applied to the next Rite, <hi>viz. The change of Cloaths.</hi> He ſhould have firſt prov'd that the Apoſtles words do certainly refer to ſuch a Religious Rite practis'd in Baptiſm to ſignifie our obligation to put off the old Man, and put on the new; and then prov'd this was a Rite meerly introdu'd by arbitrary cuſtom, without any warrant from Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For if the Apoſtles expreſſions refer to theſe two Rites as us'd to theſe purpoſes, it will be much more reaſonable to conclude that they are a part of the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and conſequently ſhould ſtill be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd and us'd by us; (unleſs we ſuppoſe that as to the <hi>former,</hi> that Maxim of our Saviour will warrant our Omiſſion of it in this colder Climate, <hi>That God will have Mercy and not Sacrifice</hi>) And on this ſuppoſition the Biſhop can draw no Argument from hence to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Feaſts of Charity</hi> and the <hi>Holy Kiſs,</hi> I do not ſee that they were <hi>Religious Rites</hi> at all, but rather real Expreſſions of their mutual Charity. If the <hi>richer</hi> ſort in a Congregation ſhould on the Lord's Day invite the <hi>poor</hi> to Dinner, this would be ſuch a real inſtance of their Love, (agreeable to our Saviour's advice about Feaſting, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.12, 13, 14.) as thoſe <hi>Feasts of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> were, but it would be no ſuch <hi>ſymbol</hi> of their <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual communion</hi> as their <hi>Feasting as the Table of the Lord</hi> is. And the ſame may moſt probably be ſaid of the <hi>Holy Kiſs,</hi> which being then a common inſtance of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Reſpect and Amity among Perſons in their <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> Aſſemblies, was therefore innocently continued in their <hi>Religious</hi> ones. As no doubt we may there pay the ſame Marks of our Reſpect and Friendſhip to each other when the Publick Worſhip is over that we do on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſions of meeting together. Nay, if we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſe <hi>two</hi> to have been Religious Rites yet it will be then more reaſonable to ſuppoſe they had a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62574:48"/> Inſtitution, than that they had no other warrant than meer arbitrary cuſtom. And upon either of theſe Suppoſitions there can be no ſhew of any Argument drawn from 'em, to prove that the Scripture warrants us to inſtitute a Religious Rite of our own, as an <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Badge whereby we are dedicated to the ſervice of a crucified Saviour,</hi> when Chriſt himſelf has inſtituted <hi>one</hi> for that uſe. For this is that which the Biſhop was concern'd to produce a ſcriptural warrant for. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may juſtly add here, that tho' the Biſhop's Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had prov'd that the Scriptures warrant us to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs our <hi>glorying in the ſufferings of Chriſt,</hi> by <hi>croſſing</hi> our ſelves as the Primitive Chriſtians did in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Converſation, yet this would not prove that they warrant us to uſe it as a Religious Rite in <hi>Baptiſm</hi> for our ſolemn Dedication to the Service of Chriſt, becauſe that is a needleſs doing that over again by a <hi>Rite</hi> of our <hi>own deviſing,</hi> which is ſufficiently done before by a Rite of <hi>Chriſt's Inſtitution.</hi> Whereas this is the thing in queſtion, and which to us looks like ſinful Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But before I diſmiſs the Argument of the Biſhop's, 'tis requiſite I ſhould conſider thoſe two ſignificant Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies among the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> which he thinks liable to the ſame Exceptions as the uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm, <hi>viz</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Their giving their Children names at their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and giving Tickets to Communicants.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For the former ſignificant Ceremony, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving names to Children at their Baptiſm, <hi>The Biſhop tells us,</hi> it ſignifies their giving up their Names to Chriſt, and engaging 'em to be his Servants. So that our Names are a laſting Token and Badge to us of our Dedication to the Service of Chriſt, and an Obligation on us to behave our ſelves accordingly.</q> 
               <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 184.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It ſeems ſomewhat ſtrange the Biſhop ſhould ſo poſitively aſſert; that we give our Children a Name at Baptiſm for any ſuch purpoſe as this. For we uſe it not as any Religious Ceremony at all, much leſs as an <hi>External Sign or Token of giving up their Names to Chriſt,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62574:48"/> and engaging 'em to be his Servants.</hi> This is all ſuggeſted by his own fancy without any ground; for we know of no other uſe of this practice in Baptiſm, then that the Perſon baptiz'd may be notified to the Congregation, by being call'd by his Name. And for the Biſhop's remark on God's giving <hi>Abraham</hi> a new Name at his Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in alluſion to the <hi>custom of Maſters giving their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants a new name upon their admiſſion into their Families;</hi> beſides that, 'tis aſſerted without any proof, (there being no ſuch reaſon, but a different one, aſſign'd by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for changing his Name from <hi>Abram</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> 17 <hi>Gen.</hi> 4, 5.) yet if it were true, I know not what uſe it can be to his purpoſe: for if he would infer from it, That this is a Scriptural warrant for giving Names to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren at Baptiſm, as a Token of their Admiſſion into God's Family, he makes it a ſignificant Ceremony of God's own appointment, and conſequently can draw no Argument from it, to juſtifie the uſe of the Croſs as a Ceremony arbitrarily appointed by Men, to ſignifie their Dedication to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For the other ſignificant Ceremony, which the Biſhop ſaith, the Diſſenters have added to the Lord's Supper, and which he deſires 'em to reflect on, viz. <hi>Giving of Tickets</hi> to ſuch as are to be admitted thereto. 'Tis, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, a very <hi>dangerous</hi> one, in which he has found out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of very ſtrange and myſterious ſignifications. For in this Ceremony he tells us, <q rend="inline">There is an outward and viſible Sign, a Ticket. <hi>Secondly,</hi> An inward Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Grace, our Aptitude and Title to the Lord's Supper and Communion of Saints, found upon our Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when we receive the Ticket. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 'Tis a Badge and Token whereby priviledg'd Members are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd from thoſe that are without. <hi>Lastly,</hi> 'Tis a ſort of neceſſary Term of Communion, ſince thoſe that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this Badge, ſhall not be admitted to the Sacrament.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If all theſe wonderful ſpiritual ſignifications aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to this poor <hi>Ticket</hi> prove meerly the product of the Biſhop's Imagination, then I hope there can be no Argument drawn from it to patroniſe the <hi>Croſs.</hi> The <hi>Ticket</hi> is I confeſs an <hi>outward and viſible ſign,</hi> but I could
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:62574:49"/> never learn before that it was a ſign of any thing more, then that the Perſon that brought it, was allow'd by the Miniſter to Communicate at that time, and did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude there without his permiſſion. But how it ſhould come to ſignifie a Man's <hi>qualifications</hi> for Receiving, or his <hi>title</hi> to any ſpiritual Benefits that belong to worthy Communicants, is very hard to conceive. All that can be ſaid of it is, that 'tis probable the Miniſter would not have given him leave to Communicate by giving him a <hi>Ticket,</hi> if he had not known him to be a Member of his <hi>own</hi> or ſome <hi>other</hi> Congregation. And the Biſhop far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſtakes in making the <hi>Ticket</hi> a <hi>Badge</hi> to diſtinguiſh priviledg'd Members from thoſe that are <hi>without;</hi> for there may be many preſent as <hi>ſpectators</hi> at Communions that are <hi>Members,</hi> and have not <hi>Tickets</hi> at preſent, becauſe they do not at preſent <hi>Receive.</hi> Nor would any Man's having a <hi>Ticket</hi> ſecure his <hi>Admiſſion,</hi> if he were known to be no <hi>Member</hi> of <hi>that</hi> or ſome <hi>other</hi> Congregation. Nay, the <hi>Ticket</hi> is no <hi>neceſſary Term of Communion</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſince no man that is a noted Member of that, or any other Congregation, would be refus'd, tho' he ſhould have no <hi>Ticket,</hi> or left it behind him. It's plain, that the giving thoſe <hi>Tickets</hi> is a circumſtance that genuinely falls within the Apoſtles Rule of <hi>doing all things decently and in order.</hi> Now in ſuch multitudes as in the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reland</hi> ordinarily frequent their Communions, there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a more eaſie and orderly expedient to diſtinguiſh the Communicants from meer Spectators, and prevent any Perſons from intruding into the Communion of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches without leave, then this of <hi>giving Tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets</hi> to ſuch as they allow to Receive at that time. So that the general Rule of Scripture foremention'd, does ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige 'em to uſe this or ſome other method of the like kind; for the <hi>decent</hi> and orderly <hi>celebration</hi> of that Holy Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and preventing the contrary <hi>confuſion</hi> and <hi>diſorder.</hi> But I hope the Biſhop will not pretend, that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>decently</hi> and <hi>orderly</hi> perform'd without uſing the ſign of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> as an <hi>Honourable Badge whereby the Perſon baptiz'd is dedicated to the ſervice of a crucified Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> and therefore the Croſs, is no way warranted by
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62574:49"/> that rule of <hi>order</hi> and <hi>decency,</hi> as the forementioned cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom evidently is. If indeed this perillous <hi>Ticket</hi> had had a <hi>Croſs</hi> upon it, and the Perſons that brought it were order'd to wear it upon their <hi>Breasts</hi> or <hi>Foreheads</hi> as a <hi>ſign</hi> whereby they publickly profeſt their <hi>Remembrance</hi> of and renewed <hi>Dedication</hi> of themſelves to the ſervice of a crucified Saviour, as the <hi>adult</hi> Members of his Church, the Biſhop might then have had ſome pretence to have compar'd theſe two cuſtoms together. But as they are really practis'd, there is no more reſemblance between 'em, then between a <hi>prudential Mode</hi> of ordering Chriſts own Inſtitution in <hi>general neceſſary,</hi> and vertually inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his own Rule of order, and an <hi>unneceſſary</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rite unwarrantably added by <hi>Man,</hi> to <hi>Christ's</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, to ſome of the ſame uſes as he had appointed another already; and any one that pleaſes may eaſily diſcern a wide difference between theſe two.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only add here, that as the Biſhop has fail'd of producing us any clear Scriptural warrant for the <hi>Croſſ,</hi> (and conſequently ought by his own Rule on that very ſcore to diſcard it as a <hi>Human Invention</hi>) ſo he has not ſo much as attempted to vindicate that other <hi>Human In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> of <hi>Godfathers</hi> and <hi>Godmothers,</hi> ſet up to exclude the Publick Promiſe of Parents, for the pious Education of their own Children, and to enter into raſh Vows, which few ever perform, which I take to be the more dangerous corruption of the two. See <hi>Remarks</hi> p. 167, 168, 169.</p>
            <p>As to the Biſhop's Concluſion I ſhall only obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I do not find that he has made good his Charge of <hi>Human Inventions</hi> againſt the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in any one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular inſtance of their Worſhip, notwithſtanding all the aſſurance wherewith he had aſſerted, <hi>Diſc.</hi> p 187. <hi>That they were ſo ſtrangely miſled as to content themſelves to meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, perhaps for ſome years with a deſign to worſhip God, when one could hardly ever ſee any thing of God's immediate appointment in their Meetings.</hi> For this the Bp. there ſaith, <hi>was manifestly the caſe of the Diſſenters in his thoughts.</hi> And he ſtill takes the ſame for granted, <hi>Admon.</hi> p. 188. <hi>That the worſhip of Diſſenters has no expreſs warrant of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62574:50"/> Scripture for it.</hi> And now to advance ſo terrible and comprehenſive a Charge, and not prove the Truth of it in any one particular Inſtance, ſeems to us a very <hi>unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed,</hi> as well as a very <hi>uncharitable</hi> attempt. Nay, 'tis ſtrange, that (except that of <hi>Croſſing</hi>) he has not ſo much as endeavour'd to vindicate one practice of the eſtabliſht Church from his own Arguments when retorted upon himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Since the Biſhop threatens us, if the Matters of Fact be diſputed, to produce his <hi>Vouchers</hi> and <hi>Authorities,</hi> we muſt now deſire him either to do ſo, or own thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes whereby he has highly injur'd the Reputation of his Brethren. And I hope he will take care that the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his <hi>Vouchers</hi> be as credible as that of thoſe I have produc'd. And he need not ſpare to produce 'em <hi>out of tenderneſs to the Diſſenters of his Dioceſe,</hi> for they deſire no other <hi>tenderneſs</hi> in this point, beſides that of ſpeaking nothing but Truth of 'em.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I think his Caution againſt the <hi>Remarks</hi> which he here gives very unfair, unleſs he had <hi>prov'd,</hi> inſtead of barely <hi>aſſerting, That my Arguments are not founded on Scripture, and that my Anſwers to his Proofs contradict the Letter of Scripture.</hi> I hope his Lordſhip will excuſe us, tho' we are unwilling to take all this for granted on no other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence than his bare word.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I hope he will find nothing in theſe Papers contrary to a <hi>ſpirit of meekneſs,</hi> or ſavouring of <hi>paſſion,</hi> And tho' the Diſſenters of his Dioceſe, cannot carry their civility to ſo high a ſtrain as to thank him for his Book, as he does them <hi>for the entertainment they have given it,</hi> yet they can readily comply with his <hi>Request</hi> to 'em, <hi>Not to be offended with him for telling 'em the truth.</hi> For the chief offence they took at his Book, was not his <hi>reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> againſt their Opinions and Practices, but his <hi>giving ſo untrue an Account</hi> of 'em. And therefore they cannot altogether aſſent to what his Lordſhip inſinuates in theſe following words: <q rend="inline">Remember nothing is more apt to provoke Mankind then Truth. And if you meet with any Book in Anſwer to mine, that diſcovers the writer to have been in a Paſſion when he wrote it, you may
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:62574:50"/> look on it as a probable Argument of the truth of what I have propos'd. And if upon reading what I have wrote, you find any motion in your ſelves towards Paſſion, conſider well whether it proceed not from the ſame cauſe, namely my declaring the truth to you.</q> For they think there is one thing more apt to provoke even the mildeſt and beſt of Men, and that is, to be unjuſtly accur'd to the world, and yet, when the Accuſer is admoniſht of his miſtakes, to have the Accuſation renew'd, and be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd to themſelves as Evidences for what they as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly know to be untrue, as they know their own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Practice. For in this caſe they think it no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Argument of Guilt in the accuſed, if they ſhould expreſs ſome juſt diſpleaſure againſt ſuch ill uſage. And yet I hope he will find even this extraordinary provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has not drawn out any language that looks like <hi>paſſion.</hi> But yet as the Bp. expects we ſhould allow <hi>plain-dealing to be a part of his character,</hi> ſo I hope he will not deny us the ſame liberty of <hi>dealing plainly</hi> with him, not only in vindicating our Opinions and Practices where we think his objections againſt 'em invalid, but eſpecially in clearing both from ſuch miſrepreſentations as we think manifeſtly groundleſs and injurious, and in deſiring an ingenuous Retraction of 'em, as an act which a regard to <hi>Juſtice</hi> as well as <hi>Truth</hi> ſhould prompt him to. For common <hi>Juſtice</hi> forbids our aſcribing to our Brethren Opinions and Practices which are none of theirs; nay, it forbids our receiving and publiſhing miſtaken Accounts of 'em, from the informations of others, when a little care and diligence might have enabled us to diſcover the falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of 'em. And conſequently the ſame Principle ſhould prompt us to do right to the Reputation of our Brethren, when we have, thro' our unwary credulity, or in the heat of oppoſition ſpoken or written of 'em what is not true, and yet what if believ'd, would tempt others to very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and uncharitable apprehenſions of their Judgment and Practice. And when his Lordſhip has given the Diſſenters of his Dioceſe this evidence of his <hi>Justice</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards 'em, they will then be more ready to believe his <hi>ſincerity in studying their good.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:62574:51"/>
            <p>And now if theſe Papers contribute any thing to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile his Lp. and thoſe whom his <hi>Book</hi> and <hi>Admonition</hi> may have miſled, to more charitable thoughts of our Worſhip, and to caution us in ſuch Debates as theſe to be more ſtrict in obſerving that excellent Rule of the Apoſtles, <hi>To ſpeak the truth in love,</hi> Eph. 4.15. I ſhall not think my pains in writing 'em wholly loſt. For tho' in the Matters in diſpute between us, it becomes every good man as to his <hi>own</hi> practice, to adhere impartially to the rule of the Holy Scriptures as far as he underſtands it; yet nothing is more plain, then that thoſe great Truths and Duties of Chriſtianity wherein we are <hi>agreed,</hi> are of incomparably greater moment and importance than thoſe wherein we <hi>differ.</hi> And as 'tis our unity in thoſe more important Truths and Duties that chiefly <hi>recommends</hi> us to the acceptance of <hi>our bleſſed Lord;</hi> ſo that alone is ſufficient to <hi>endear</hi> us to <hi>one another;</hi> and for thoſe ſmaller <hi>Differences</hi> among us that are ſo fully conſiſtent with a happy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in theſe eſſentials of our Religion, however they may now diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh us into <hi>Parties,</hi> yet they can never be reaſonably thought to exclude the Churches on either ſide from the Communion of the <hi>Church Catholick;</hi> much leſs will they exclude the truly pious Members on either ſide from the <hi>Heavenly Society.</hi> How little then ſhould thoſe <hi>Differences</hi> tend to <hi>diſunite</hi> our <hi>affections,</hi> or to obſtruct our amicable endeavours to advance the common Intereſt of <hi>Practical Holineſs?</hi> how ſhould we rejoyce to ſee that bleſſed work proſper in each others hands? how entirely ſhould Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty govern all our debates in the points wherein we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree, and make us unwilling to miſrepreſent each others opinions or practices, when we calmly reaſon againſt 'em? how ſtrongly ſhould it prompt us to treat each other in all reſpects as brethren, in whom we behold the image of our great Maſter ſtampt, tho' we may not ſee the inſcription of this or that party, which we judge to be the moſt happily reform'd, or the beſt conſtituted and modell'd? how much more zealous ſhould we be to <hi>proſelyte</hi> Men to the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of Religion, then to any external <hi>Modes</hi> of Worſhip and Diſcipline? And how heartily ſhould we joyn in that <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Benediction, <hi>Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity, Amen.</hi> 6 Eph. 24.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:62574:51"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Sinclare's</hi> Letter referred to <hi>p.</hi> 14.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Argumentative and Historical parts of the Biſhop of <hi>Derry's</hi> Admonition, ſeem both of a piece as to the many apparent miſtakes in 'em. A ſatisfactory Anſwer to the former is juſtly expected from your ſelf. But for the latter, as its neceſſary to make uſe of the Information of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who, I am confident, will be more faithful to you, thou the Biſhop's Informers have been to him: ſo I ſhall readily comply with your deſire, to give a true and certain account of the practice of Diſſenters in <hi>Waterford</hi> before the late Troubles; which was ſo very different from that which his Lordſhip gives, when he ſays, <hi>p. 32. He had opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to enquire, and was told they did not Communicate above once a year, if ſo often:</hi> That (as he hath taught us in the <hi>former page</hi>) we may thence conclude the proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of what he ſays concerning others.</p>
            <p>This account I'm more concerned and better enabled to give you with greater aſſurance, becauſe I preach'd to 'em at that time, and have alſo carefully preſerv'd a Memorial of ſuch things in my <hi>Diary,</hi> which are as followeth.</p>
            <p>I was Ordain'd a Paſtor to that People about a year and a half before the Troubles, and Administred the Lords Supper five times in thirteen Months of that time, viz. <hi>Decemb. 18. 1687. May 6. 1688. July 1. 88. Oct. 28. 88. Jan. 27. 88.</hi> beſides four times more I Adminiſtred that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament the ſame year to another Congregation, that was ſupplied by ſome neighbouring Miniſters and my ſelf. And I can aſſure you, that thoſe Ministers gave the Communion more frequently, moſt of 'em <hi>once a Month,</hi> ſome of <hi>'em once in two Months</hi> to their own Congregations.</p>
            <p>But that I may conceal nothing from you, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's Information may poſſibly be ſuppoſed to reach unto, I ſhall acquaint you, that tho' the Diſſenters in <hi>Waterford,</hi> both before I came among 'em, and while I preach'd to 'em only as a Candidate, had no fixed Pastor, yet even then they had the Communion Adminiſtred to 'em <hi>oftner than once a year,</hi> by ſome of the aforeſaid Miniſters that us'd to viſit them for that end, and many of the People us'd alſo to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate frequently with theſe Miniſters in their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62574:52"/>
            <p>I ſhall further ſuggeſt to you, that the reaſon of my preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to 'em for ſome time as a <hi>Candidate</hi> only, was the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme diſcouragement I met with there from the ſeverities of ſome that call'd themſelves <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> for we were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently diſturb'd in our publick worſhip, and <hi>6</hi> times forc't to change the place of our Meeting: the beſt part of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory was for a whole Sabbath detain'd priſoners by armed men, and towards evening, I was convey'd by a ſtrong Guard thro' a throng of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who rejoyc'd to ſee <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that drudgery for 'em; and ſeveral times beſides that, I was brought before the Magiſtrate, and inſtead of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, was only revil'd and threatned. But at laſt they attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the common practice of that time, to accuſe me of Plots and when they were ſhamefully diſappointed and vented their rage againſt me, the then <hi>Mayor</hi> hardly reſcued me from 'em. But ſoon after another <hi>Mayor</hi> ſucceeded that was for their purpoſe, and joyn'd with ſome of 'em, to expoſe me after this manner: The Military Governour rudely aſſulted me in the <hi>Mayor</hi>'s houſe (where I came to ſee ſome friends take horſe, for he kept a publick Inn) and dragg'd me into the streets, where the Soldiers received mo, the rude Officers pull'd off my Hat, and forced me to go bare-headed thro' the chief parts of the City, with two Drums tabering before me, till they ſent me over the River, with a threatning Meſſage to the Inns on the other ſide, if they ſhould dare to entertain me. This forc'd me to complain to the L. <hi>Clarendon</hi> then L. Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, who being fully convinc'd of my Perſecutors malice, and the miſeries I had ſuffer'd gave his Order that I ſhould return peaceably to my habitation, and be ſafely protected in it. And having then ſome hope of eaſe from the violence of my adverſaries, I accepted the call of the people and was Ordain'd, among 'em by ſome of the neighbouring Ministers, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred the Communion for the time I continued with 'em as is above-mention'd; and I am aſſur'd that the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation hath the Sacrament administred to 'em <hi>6 times a year</hi> by their preſent Pastor Mr. <hi>Cock.</hi> This I judge ſufficient to vindicate our practice from what we are accuſed of, and being a Matter of Fact ſo generally known. I could produce many witneſſes (if it were needful) to confirm this Testimony of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>your Affectionate Brother and Servant, <hi>Alexander Sinclare.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:62574:52"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Biſhop's Introduction conſider'd, p. 1</item>
               <item>His Three Heads examin'd.</item>
               <item>1. That relating to the Motives of writing his Book, from p. 4. to 7</item>
               <item>2. That relating to the Conceſſions made in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks. p. 7. to 9</item>
               <item>3. That relating to Matters of Fact, from p. 8, to 38</item>
               <item>His other Exceptions againſt the Remarks conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd.</item>
               <item>Two relating to the Author examin'd, p. 37. to 40</item>
               <item>That relating to the Rule of Worſhip which the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop pretends to be laid down in the Remarks, anſwer'd from p. 40. to 48</item>
               <item>His Exception againſt the Requeſts offer'd to the Conf. Clergy Anſwer'd, from p. 48. to 53</item>
               <item>His Exceptions relating to what the Remarks object againſt the Croſs in Baptiſm.</item>
               <item>The Biſhop's Objections againſt the Directory in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Baptiſm, conſider'd from p. 53. to 58</item>
               <item>The Argument propos'd in the Remarks againſt the Croſs, more fully ſtated, from p. 58. to 73.</item>
               <item>The Biſhop's Anſwer to this Argument examined. p. 73. to 76</item>
               <item>The Biſhop's Argument to prove the uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm warranted by Scripture, anſwered from p. 76. to 86</item>
               <item>Remarks on the Biſhop's Concluſion.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Sinclare</hi>'s Letter concerning the Practice of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters in <hi>Waterford,</hi> as to the frequency of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:62574:53"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>WHereas the Biſhop, <hi>Admon. p. 69.</hi> aſſerts, <hi>That ſome, who have been found unqualified and inſufficient for Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by them, are receiv'd as Preachers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Diſſenters, after being rejected by them.</hi> And adds, <hi>That he has a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Example thereof ſince he came to this Dioceſe.</hi> The Diſſenting Miniſters of his Dioceſe Declare they know of no ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And if the Biſhop (as there is ſome ground to conjecture) mean Mr. <hi>Sq.</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares he was never Examin'd as to his Learning by them; and (beſides that, he is no Preacher in that part of the Kingdom) moſt that know him) think that if his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſhould reject all thoſe of his Clergy that are not Mr. <hi>Sq.</hi>'s Superiours in Learning, he muſt exclude a great many of thoſe that are now in his Dioceſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62574:53"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
